安妮・弗兰克日记
主演
米丽・帕金斯
制片，导演：
乔治・斯蒂文斯
弗兰克先生
Mr. Frank.
弗兰克先生？
Mr. Frank?
卡勒？
Kraler?
卡勒先生
Mr. Kraler.
米耶普
Miep.
我的好朋友
My good friends.
噢，很......
Oh, it...
很高兴见到你回家
it is so good to see you home.
我们没得到任何消息
We had heard nothing.
我就一个人
I'm alone.
你得和我们一起回家
You must come home with us...
现在去休息
and rest now.
-你必须和我们呆在一起，   -不，米耶普，我不能留在阿姆斯特丹
- You must stay with us. - No, Miep. I can't stay in Amsterdam.
弗兰克先生，这里是你的家
Mr. Frank, this is your home.
阿姆斯特丹是你的家
Amsterdam is your home.
这里让我回忆起太多了
It has too many memories for me.
到处触景伤情，到处
Everywhere there's something, Miep. Everywhere.
甚至见到你和卡勒先生的时候
Even seeing you and Mr. Kraler.
原谅我，你们做了那么多，我不该这样和你们说话
Forgive me. I shouldn't talk to you like this after all that you did.
我们还会那么做的
We would do it again.
什么都没有了--那本书
Everything's gone-- the book.
他们拿走了一切
They took everything...
除了一些文件
except some papers.
我们保存了你的信件和文件
We saved your letters and papers.
请把那些烧掉
Please burn them.
烧掉所有东西
Burn everything.
我...... 我......
I... I...
告诉安妮，如果我回来，我会找到她的书
told Anne if I got back here, I'd find her book.
安妮日记？那就是她留下那本书的地方
Anne's diary? It's where she left it.
"1942年7月9日"
"The ninth of July, 1942."
1942年，有可能吗，米耶普？
1942. Is it possible, Miep?
才3年前
Only three years ago.
"亲爱的日记，自从你我要成为最好的朋友......
"Dear Diary, since you and I are going to be great friends...
我就要告诉你我所有的一切了
"I will start by telling you all about myself.
我叫安妮・弗兰克
"My name is Anne Frank.
13岁
"I am 1 3 years old.
我生在德国
"I was born in Germany...
但是因为我家是犹太人......
"but since my family is Jewish...
在希特勒上台后，我们移民到了荷兰
"we emigrated to Holland when Hitler came to power.
我们的一切都开始好转
Things went well for us...
直到战争降临，德国占领了这里
"until the war came,and the German occupation.
犹太人的处境变得很差
"Then things got very bad for the Jews.
不可以做这个，不可以做那个
You could not do this, and you could not do that.
我们必须佩戴黄色星星标志
We had to wear yellow stars.
我必须上缴我的自行车
I had to turn in my bike.
我再也不能去荷兰人的学校
I couldn't go to a Dutch school anymore.
不能看电影，不能坐小汽车......
I couldn't go to the movies or ride in an automobile...
甚至不能坐公车
or even on a streetcar...
还有无数其他的事情
and a million other things.
但是不管怎样，我们小孩还是尽力快活起来
but somehow we children still managed to have fun.
今天早晨爸爸5点就叫醒我......
This morning father woke me at 5:00...
他告诉我快点起来穿衣服
and told me to hurry and get dressed.
我们要去躲起来
We were going into hiding.
我要穿上尽可能多的衣服
I was to put on as many clothes as I could.
如果我们带着箱子出去，会引起怀疑
It would look too suspicious if we walked along carrying suitcases.
我们要消失......
We were going to disappear...
在空气中蒸发
vanish into thin air.
我活在冒险中
I'm living a great adventure.
还有3个人和我们一起
Three other people were coming in with us.
爸爸认识他们，但是我从来没有见过他们
father knew them, but we had never met them.
一定发生什么事了
Something's happened.
他们得徒步走3英里
They have three miles to walk.
-妈妈......  -我知道他们被抓了
- Mother...   - They've been arrested. I know.
-你们能停下吗？   -妈妈！爸爸！
- Will you stop that? - Mother! father!
我们在这儿
We're here.
都到了吗？
See?
-范・戴恩先生  -你好，你好
- Mr. Van Daan. - Hello, hello.
-范・戴恩太太。彼得。  -弗兰克先生
- Mrs. Van Daan. Peter. - Mr. Frank.
大街上到处都是环保警察
There were too many of the Green Police on the streets.
我们必须绕远
We had to take the long way around.
介绍自己了吗？这是我女儿安妮，我妻子埃蒂茨
Did you introduce yourself? My daughter Anne. My wife Edith.
-玛戈特。范・戴恩先生太太。  -你好
- Margot. Mr. and Mrs. Van Daan. - Hello.
-噢，这是我们的儿子彼得
Oh, and this is our son Peter.
那么，请，让我们脱下一部分衣服
So, now, please, let us take off some of these clothes.
早上好
Good morning.
-早上好，卡勒先生。  --早上好，卡勒先生。
- Hello, Mr. Kraler. - Good morning, Mr. Kraler.
弗兰克先生。啊，你们都在这儿，不错。
Mr. Frank. Ah, you're all here. That is good.
我们本来希望做的有条不紊
We had hoped to have everything in order.
卡勒先生，请不要那么想
Please, Mr. Kraler, don't even think of it.
要知道，我们有足够空闲时间安排我们的一切
After all, we'll have plenty of leisure to arrange everything ourselves.
-我带了些三明治做你们的午餐。   -谢谢，米耶普
- I brought sandwiches for your lunch. - Thank you, Miep.
灌装食物在这儿，还有你们要储存的干豆和马铃薯
The canned goods are here, and your stores of dried beans and potatoes.
-我下午把定量供给证拿来。   -定量供给证？
- I'll get ration books this afternoon. - Ration books?
如果他们看到供给证上有我们的名字，就会知道我们在这里了
If they see our names on ration books, they'll know we're here.
别担心，上边不会写你们的名字
Don't worry. It won't be your names that'll be on them.
爸爸！西部教堂！
father! The Westertoren!
安妮，不！
Anne, no!
永远不要碰那扇窗帘，永远不要.
You must never touch a curtain. Never.
任何人都不可以碰窗帘，无论白天还是晚上
No one must ever touch a curtain, day or night.
要是街上有人向上看，或者对面房子中有人看到......
If someone on the street should look up, or someone in those houses should see...
我们就毁了
we would be lost.
请记住，这不仅仅是对我们自己性命攸关...
Please remember, it's not only our lives that are at stake...
而且也关系到米耶普和卡勒先生的性命
but also Miep's and Mr. Kraler's.
-你只有13分钟安顿一下。  -谢谢
- You have but 1 3 minutes to get settled. - Thank you.
米耶普和我会每天上来一次，给你们带来食物和消息。米耶普，我们必须走了
Miep or I will be up each day to bring you food and news. Miep, we must go.
再见
Good-bye for now.
真不知道怎样谢谢你们
How can we thank you?
我永远也想不到还有......
I never thought I'd live to see the day...
象弗兰克先生这样的人竟然也躲起来的时候
when a man like Mr. Frank would have to go into hiding.
当你想想......
When you think of the...
-再见     -谢谢，卡勒先生
- Good-bye. - Thank you, Mr. Kraler.
-再见，米耶普。   --再见
- Good-bye, Miep. - Good-bye.
-再见
Good-bye.
-安妮！   -好了，我多穿了3件
- Anne! - It's all right. I have on three more.
打扰一下，弗兰克先生
Excuse me, Mr. Frank.
他什么意思，只有13分钟？
What did he mean, just 13 minutes?
是指工人到来之前
Before the workmen come.
各位，当下面的楼里有人的时候......
Now, while the men are in the building below...
我们必须保持绝对安静
we must have complete quiet.
任何声音下面都会听到......
Every sound can be heard down there...
不但办公室，车间也会听到
not only in the offices but in the workrooms too.
人们大概8点半到，5点半离开
The men come at about 8:30, they leave at about 5:30...
所以，为了绝对安全，从早上8点到晚上6点......
so to be perfectly safe, from 8:00 in the morning until 6:00 in the evening...
除非万不得已，我们才可以在这儿四处走动......
we must move about up here only when it is absolutely necessary...
而且一定要穿着长袜
and then in stocking feet.
我们只能轻声低语，不可以放水
We must not speak above a whisper. We must not run any water.
我们不可以用水池甚至--抱歉--厕所
We cannot use the sink or even-- forgive me-- the W.C.
那些管道通向下面的车间
The pipes go down through the workrooms.
-垃圾也不可以......
- No trash must ever be
垃圾也不可以扔出去，因为可能暴露有人住在这里
No trash must ever be thrown out which might reveal someone is living up here.
即使一块土豆皮
Not even a potato peeling.
我们必须在晚上把所有东西烧掉
We must burn everything in this stove at night.
这就是我们必须过的日子，直到一切都结束，如果我们还活着的话
This is the way that we must live until it is over, if we are to survive.
直到一切都结束
Until it is over.
6点之后我们可以自由活动
After 6:00 we can move about.
我们可以说笑，吃晚餐，阅读，做游戏......
We can talk and laugh, have our supper, read, play games...
就像平时在家里一样
just as we would at home.
现在，最明智的是请我们都回到自己的房间，8点前安顿好
Now it would be wise if we all went to our rooms and were settled before 8:00.
范・戴恩太太，你和你丈夫住楼上
Mrs. Van Daan, you and your husband will be upstairs.
很遗憾上面没有彼得的地方......
I regret that there's no place up there for Peter...
但是他可以住这，我们旁边
but he'll be here, near us.
-那我住哪儿？  -和玛戈特住那里边
- And where am I? - You and Margot will be in there.
-打扰一下，弗兰克先生。  -什么事？
-Excuse me, Mr. Frank. - Yes?
-你和弗兰克太太睡哪儿？  -这个房间也是我们的卧室
- Where do you and Mrs. Frank sleep? - This room is also our bedroom.
哦，不，你们住楼上。
Oh, no. You take the upstairs.
-没关系，那是你们的地方。  -我们住下边吧
- It's not right. It's your place. - We'll sleep down here.
我已经考虑过了，这是最好的安排。唯一的安排
I've thought this out. It's the best arrangement. The only arrangement.
呃，埃蒂茨？
Uh, Edith?
嗯？
Hmm?
你得休息了，亲爱的
You must have some rest, dear.
你昨晚一夜没合眼
You didn't close your eyes last night.
-和玛戈特去孩子们的房间。  -安妮，你呢？
- Go in the girls' room with Margot. - How about Anne?
我很好，我帮帮爸爸
I feel fine. I'm going to help father.
请这边走，范・戴恩太太
This way, Mrs. Van Daan.
抱歉
Excuse me.
从这儿上去
Up here.
弗兰克先生
Mr. Frank.
-弗兰克先生？    -彼得？
- Mr. Frank? - Peter?
-我可以给我的猫弄些水吗？  -你有猫？
-Do I have time to get water for my cat? -Have you got a cat?
去吧，但是轻点。你只有5分钟
Go ahead, but be quick. You only have five minutes.
没有猫他就没法活
He couldn't live without that cat.
我不知道你有猫
I didn't know you had a cat.
我爱猫
I love cats.
-它叫什么名字？   -毛刺
- What's its name? - Mouschi.
是什么？毛刺。公的还是母的？
What is it? Mouschi. A him or her?
公的。它不喜欢生人
It's a tom, and it doesn't like strangers.
那么，我必须尽快和它熟悉，是吗？会拴住它吗？
Well, I'll have to stop being a stranger, won't I? Is he fixed?
不会
No.
哦，你应该拴住它，避免它打架
Well, you ought to have him fixed to keep him from fighting.
多好看的猫啊
What a nice cat.
你在哪儿上学?
Where do you go to school?
犹太中学
Jewish Secondary.
我和玛戈特也在那里上学
That's where Margot and I go.
嗯，我知道
Yeah, I know.
过去从来没见过你啊
I've never seen you around.
我有时候会见到你
I used to see you sometimes.
你见过？
You did?
但是为什么你那时候不过来
But why didn't you ever come over?
哦，我也不知道。我是那种独来独往的人
Oh, I don't know. I'm sort of a lone wolf.
这竟然有一条孤独的狼
Can't be a lone wolf here.
我真想知道我们今天没露面，我们的朋友会说什么？
Wonder what our friends will say when we don't show up today?
我和珊妮约过时间
I had a date with Sanne.
你认识珊妮・德・沃瑞斯吗？
Do you know Sanne de Vries?
-不认识。  -珊妮是我最好的朋友
- No. - Sanne's my best friend.
她和我一样瘦
She's thin like me.
他们总是对我们起哄：“安妮和珊妮，两根细麻杆。”
They always yell at us, "'Anne and Sanne, the skinny bananas. '"
把你的星星摘下吧
You took off your star.
好
That's right.
不可以，如果你不佩戴星星出去，他们会逮捕你
You can't do that. They'll arrest you if you go out without your star.
谁会出去啊？
Who's going out?
帮一下
Help me.
-我来帮忙
- I'm helping.
-你怎么处理它？  -烧掉
- What are you going to do with it? - Burn it.
太有趣了。我可不能烧掉我的
That's funny. I don't think I could burn mine.
我也不知道原因
I don't know why.
你不能？那个他们逼你带上然后鄙视你的东西？
You couldn't? Something they make you wear so they can kick you around?
我知道
I know.
但是，毕竟这是大卫之星，不是吗？
But, after all, it is the Star of David, isn't it?
安妮，快8点了
Annele? It's almost 8:00.
彼得，你不想过来和我们坐在一起吗？马上就是漫长的一天了
Don't you want to come and sit with us, Peter? It's going to be a long day.
不，谢谢，这就可以
No, thanks. This is fine.
别忘了脱下鞋，记住
You won't forget to take off your shoes, will you?
彼得
Peter.
很高兴你能和我们在一起
It's nice to have you with us.
嗯，弗兰克先生
Yes, Mr. Frank.
回见
See you later.
-他在同一所学校......
- He went to the same school that...
有一种很欣慰的感觉，一想到卡勒先生和他的秘书......
It's comforting to think Mr. Kraler and his secretary...
就在我们下面的办公室里
are down there below us in the offiice.
我们称呼他们是“我们的保护人”
Our protectors, we call them.
我问过爸爸，到底会发生什么样的事情，要是有人发现......
I asked father what would happen to them if anyone found out...
他们藏匿了我们
they were hiding us.
爸爸说他们会遭受和我们同样的命运
father said they would suffer the same fate that we would.
我们是在一个老调料工厂上面
We are over an old spice factory.
你可以闻到整个楼弥漫着香料味道
You can smell the spices all through the building.
那一天我是读着《双城记》度过的
I read A Tale of Two Cities through in that first day.
和我以往曾经做过的相比......
"It is a far, far better thing I do...
没有比这更好的事情了
"than I have ever done.
和我以往所知道的相比......
"It is a far, far better rest that I go to...
没有比这更好的休息了
"than I have ever known.
结束
The end. '"
这是我读过的最悲惨的书
It was the saddest book I ever read.
是我们，米耶普和卡勒
It is us, Miep and Kraler.
晚上好，卡勒先生。晚上好，米耶普
Good evening, Mr. Kraler. Good evening, Miep.
-晚上好，安妮。   -你好，你好
- Evening, Annele. - Hello. Hello.
你好
Hello.
-哦，弗兰克先生。  -哦？
- Oh, Mr. Frank. - Yes?
-这个是你要的盒子。  -谢谢
- This is the box you asked for. - Thank you.
-晚上好，卡勒先生。   -朋友们，你们在这上面真安静
- Good evening, Mr. Kraler. - My friends, you are so quiet up here.
我都以为你们出去散步了
I thought you'd gone out for a walk.
你能想象到我一句话都没说吗？
Can you imagine me? I didn't talk.
我一天几乎都没动。我希望他们在学校能听到我说的
I hardly moved for one whole day. I wish they could hear that at school.
毛刺！毛刺！
Mouschi! Mouschi!
彼得！
Peter!
毛刺！
Mouschi!
-嘘！    -嘘，安妮
- Shh! - Shh. Annele.
-安妮！   彼得，我警告你
- Annele! - Peter, I'm warning you.
请安静。玛戈特，玛戈特！
Please, quiet. Margot. Margot.!
-这些是什么？   -不必小声说话
- What are these? - You don't have to whisper.
哦，给你
Oh, there you are.
一只漂亮的猫
It's such a nice cat.
谢谢
Thank you.
不客气
You're welcome.
安妮。盒子在这儿
Annele. There's a box there.
打开好吗？
Will you open it, please?
你知道我是怎样看这里的吗？
You know how I'm going to think of it here?
一个提供饭食的公寓，非常独特的公寓
As a boardinghouse. A very peculiar boardinghouse.
爸爸，我的影星！
father, my film stars!
我一直在想他们在哪里
I was wondering where they were.
威廉敏娜女王。太棒了
And Queen Wilhelmina. How wonderful.
还有呢
There's something more.
快，再看看
Go on. Look further.
日记本
A diary.
我从来没有过日记本......
I've never had a diary...
我一直想要一个
and I've always wanted one.
哦
Ohh.
铅笔？
A pencil?
我下楼去拿根铅笔
I'm going downstairs to get a pencil.
-安妮，不可以。   -现在下面没有人啊
- Anne, no. - But there's nobody down there now.
那不重要。任何时候不要走过那扇门
It doesn't matter. Don't ever go beyond that door.
-任何时候？   -永不
- Ever? - Never.
对不起，安妮。那不安全
I'm sorry, Anne. It isn't safe.
-我知道了。  -我知道很难
- I see. - It'll be hard. I know that.
但是要一直记住，安妮：
But always remember this, Anneke:
没有任何人可以把墙，锁头，门闩放在你心头
there are no walls, no locks, no bolts that anyone can put on your mind.
事实上，只有我们之间，安妮
As a matter of fact, just between us, Annele...
在这里对你有好处
being here has certain advantages for you.
还记得那次因为套鞋你和你妈妈吵架吗？
Remember that battle you had with your mother on the subject of overshoes?
你说要是穿套鞋你宁可去死
You said you'd rather die than wear overshoes.
记得吗？发生什么事了？
Remember?Well, what happened?
最后，你还得穿上
In the end, you had to wear them.
现在，在这里你一直不必穿套鞋了
Now, for as long as we are here you won't have to wear overshoes.
那不好吗？
Isn't that good?
还有钢琴？
And the piano?
你再也不用练习钢琴了
You won't have to practice on the piano.
告诉你，这对于你会是很美好的生活
I tell you, this is going to be a fine life for you.
记日记对于像我这样的人来说，是一个很奇特的想法
It's an odd idea for someone like me to keep a diary.
不仅仅是因为我过去从来没有记过......
Not only because I have never done so before...
而且还因为对于我来说，似乎我本人，还有与此相关的其他人......
but because it seems to me that neither I, nor for that matter anyone else...
没有谁会对一个13岁小女孩吐露的秘密感兴趣
will be interested in the unbosomings of a 13-year-old schoolgirl.
不过，那重要吗？
Still, what does that matter?
我要写下来
I want to write.
更重要的是......
but more than that...
我要呈现出所有......
I want to bring out all kinds of things...
深深埋在我心底的东西
that lie buried deep in my heart.
首先，我希望能描述出......
First of all, I expect I should be describing...
躲藏起来是什么样的感觉
what it's like to go into hiding.
但是除了我自己的感受，我还一无所知
but I don't really know yet myself.
我只知道从不到外面去有点不舒服
I only know it's funny never to be able to go outdoors...
从不呼吸新鲜空气......
never to breathe fresh air...
从不奔跑，不呼唤，不跳跃
never to run and shout and jump.
1942年9月23日，星期三
Wednesday, the 23rd of September, 1942.
战争消息很好
The news of the war is good.
斯大林格勒还在坚持
Stalingrad is still holding out.
俄国人的攻势在莫斯科地区展开
The Russian offensive continues in the Moscow area.
-安全了，最后一个工人离开了。  -耶！
- It's safe. The last workman has left. - Whee!
-安妮！   -我第一个去厕所
- Anne! - I'm first for the W.C.
现在是6点，玛戈特，学校放学了
It's 6:00, Margot. School is over.
我的鞋在哪里？
Where are my shoes?
看到我的鞋了吗？
Have you seen my shoes?
-什么鞋？   -你应该不好意思
- What shoes?  - You're gonna be sorry.
-我？   -安妮宝贝
- I am? - Anne dear.
-等我给你拿。  -我等着
- Wait till I get you. - I'm waiting.
停！彼得，嗷！
Stop! Peter. Ouch!
安妮！彼得！
Anne! Peter!
嘿，你去哪儿？
Hey, where are you going?
给毛刺拿晚饭
Going to give Mouschi his dinner.
彼得！
Peter!
安妮宝贝，我想你不该像那样和彼得玩
Anne dear, I think you shouldn't play like that with Peter.
那不好看
It's not dignified.
谁要什么好看不好看？我才不要什么好看
Who wants to be dignified? I don't want to be dignified.
你总是怨我不把你当成大人，但是我真的把你当成大人，你又怨我
You complain that I don't treat you like a grown-up, but when I do you resent it.
我只是找些乐趣而已
I only want some fun.
我不知道和那个男孩一起又怎样
I don't know what's the matter with that boy.
给他一点时间吧，他还不习惯女孩
Give him a little time. He isn't used to girls.
时间？不是已经两个月了吗？
Time? Isn't two months time?
我都想哭
I could cry.
我真奇怪米耶普在哪里。她一般很及时来的
I wonder where Miep is. She's usually so prompt.
玛戈特，来和我一起跳舞吧
Margot, come and dance with me, please.
我还有些事要做，安妮
I've got more work to do, Anne.
你看，我们都快忘了怎样跳舞了
You know, we're going to forget how to dance.
当我们出去的时候，什么都会忘了
When we get out, we won't remember a thing.
彼得在哪儿？
Where's Peter?
他能在哪儿？和他的猫在一起呗
Where would he be? With his cat.
他还没做完功课，是吗？
He hasn't finished his lessons, has he?
彼得
Peter.
-彼得！   -那是什么？
- Peter! - What is it?
你妈妈让你出去
Your mother says to come out!
我在给毛刺吃晚饭，我在喂我的猫
I'm giving Mouschi his dinner. I'm feeding my cat.
你记得你爸爸一直说你在那只猫身上浪费了所有时间
You know what your father says about you wasting all your time with that cat.
-我午饭后就没见到他。  -我告诉你了
- I haven't looked at him since lunch. - I'm only telling you.
我要喂猫
I'll feed him.
出去，我要你别进来，我是说出去
You stay out of here. And I mean out.
你就这么和你这个小女朋友说话吗？
Is that any way for you to talk to your little girlfriend?
妈妈......
Mother...
我问过你，不要那样说话可以吗？
I asked you, would you please not say that?
看，他脸红了
Look, he's blushing.
他脸红了
He's blushing.
哦，我不会那样了，不过......能让我单独呆会吗
Please. I'm not, but... Leave me alone, will you.
你都说什么了？你的举动就好像做错什么了
What did I say? You act like it's something to be ashamed of.
有个小女朋友没什么可害臊的
It's nothing to be ashamed of to have a little girlfriend.
-真是疯了。她才13岁。  -什么？你16岁了，正合适
- That's crazy. She's only 13. - So what? You're 16. It's just perfect.
你爸爸比我大10岁
Your father is 10 years older than I.
弗兰克先生，我得警告你，这场战争还要持续很长时间，我们要成亲戚了
Mr. Frank, I warn you, this war lasts much longer, we're gonna be related.
恭喜你
Mazel tov.
午饭后我就没见到我的猫
I haven't seen my cat since lunch.
我在喂毛刺晚饭
I'm giving Mouschi his dinner.
我的小毛刺
My little Mouschi.
没有我珍贵的毛刺，我可没法活
I couldn't live without my precious Mouschi.
你奇妙的猫，你！
You wonderful cat, you!
是的，呱呱小姐
All right, Miss Quack-Quack.
-说什么？  -呱呱小姐！
- What's that? - Miss Quack-Quack!
没听说你在班里那么能说吗？他们叫你呱呱小姐
Heard about how you talk so much in class, they call you Miss Quack-Quack.
你太让人受不了了，你是我见过的最让人受不了的男孩！
You're the most intolerable, insufferable boy I ever met!
呱-呱-呱！
Quack-quack-quack!
-我会让你好看的！  -呱！
- I'll give it to you good! - Quack!
嗷！
Ooh!
安妮宝贝，你很热
Anne dear, you're hot.
你有点热。感觉好点了吗？
You're warm. Are you feeling all right?
-妈妈，请。  -你没发烧吧？
- Mother, please. - You don't have a fever, do you?
-没有。  -你知道在这儿可不能叫医生
- No. - You know we can't call a doctor here.
只有一件事可做：小心预防
There's only one thing to do: watch carefully.
得病之前就预防好。让我看看你舌头
Prevent an illness before it comes. Let me see your tongue.
妈妈，这太荒唐了
Mother, this is perfectly absurd.
安妮宝贝，别像个小孩似的
Anne dear, don't be such a baby.
让我看看你舌头
Let me see your tongue.
-奥托。  -安妮
- Otto. - Anne.
-听你妈妈的话。  -快点，张开嘴
- You hear your mother, don't you? - Come on, open up.
呱
Quack.
安妮
Anne.
-奥托。  -安妮
- Otto. - Anne.
你没事
You're all right.
我想我们的安妮也没有什么大不了的病，就像骑上自行车......
I think there's nothing the matter with our Anne that a ride on her bike...
或者和她的朋友珊妮・德・沃瑞斯的旅游治不了的病
or a visit with her friend Sanne de Vries wouldn't cure.
是那样吗,安妮?
Isn't that so, Annele?
我一直希望彼得是个女孩......
I keep wishing that Peter was a girl...
而不是个男孩
instead of a boy.
那样我就有可以说话的了
Then I'd have someone to talk to.
世界上那么多男孩......
With all the boys in the world...
为什么我偏偏要锁定他呢？
why did I have to get locked up with him?
有人吗？
Is it someone?
是米耶普
Is it Miep?
我们没听到，真怪
It's strange we don't hear.
或许她受伤了――高射炮
Maybe she got hurt-- the flak.
-她会来的。  -我希望她来
- She'll come. - I wish she'd get here.
没有烟我都快疯了
I'm going crazy without cigarettes.
安妮，今天的历史卷子你得了个“优”
Anne, you got an "excellent" in your history paper today...
拉丁语得了个“良”
and a "very good" in Latin.
噢，那代数呢？
Yes, but how about algebra?
有件事要坦白了
Well, I have a confession to make.
到现在我一直在努力领先你代数
Up until now I managed to stay ahead of you in algebra.
今天你赶上我了
Today you caught up with me.
我们留给玛戈特改正吧
We'll leave it to Margot to correct.
-你不感觉代数太恶心了吗，爸爸？  -恶心
- Isn't algebra vile, father? - Vile.
我做的怎么样啊？
How did I do?
-当然优秀了。  安妮，安妮，请
- Excellent, of course. - Anne, Anne, please.
你今天的法语作文太好了，太好了
Your French composition today was wonderful,just wonderful.
范・戴恩太太，我可以试穿一下吗？
Mrs. Van Daan, may I try it on?
不，安妮
No, Anne.
可以的
It's all right. Really.
但是当心点
But please, be careful with it.
我爸爸去世那年送给我的这件大衣
My father gave me this coat the year before he died.
他总是送给我钱可以买到的最好东西
He always bought me the best money could buy.
范・戴恩太太，你过去是不是有很多男朋友......
Mrs. Van Daan, did you have a lot of boyfriends...
就是在你结婚以前？
before you were married?
安妮，那是私人问题
Anne, that's a personal question.
问私人问题不礼貌
It's not courteous to ask personal questions.
我不介意
I don't mind.
安妮，我们的房子总是招来一群男孩
Anneke, our house was always swarming with boys.
-当我还是个年轻女孩的时候......  -哦，不，已经不再是了
- When I was a young girl... - Oh, no. Not again.
住嘴！
Shut up!
一年夏天，我们在希尔沃森有一所大房子
One summer we had a big house in Hilversum.
那些男孩......
The boys...
那些男孩跑来嗡嗡，就像蜜蜂围着蜜罐
The boys would come buzzing around like bees around a jam pot.
当我17岁的时候......
When I was 17...
呵，我们那时穿的裙子非常短的......
Well, we were wearing our skirts very short in those days...
我有一双漂亮的腿
and I had such good-looking legs.
现在也是。我可能不如过去漂亮了，但是我的腿仍然漂亮
I still have. I may not be as pretty as I used to be, but I still have my legs.
你看怎么样，弗兰克先生？
How about it, Mr. Frank?
是的，是的。我们看到了
All right, all right. We see them.
没问你。我再问弗兰克先生
I'm not asking you. I'm asking Mr. Frank.
妈妈，看在老天的份上
Mother, for heaven's sakes.
噢，让你也尴尬了，是吗？
Oh, I embarrass you too, do I?
我只是希望你也找个那么漂亮的
Well, I only hope the girl you marry has as good.
安妮，我爸爸很为我担心，因为那些男孩晃来晃去
Anneke, my father used to worry about me with all the boys hanging around.
他常对我说：“要是哪个男孩对你调情......
And he used to say to me, "If any of those boys get fresh...
“你就对他说......
"you just say to him...
“记住，某某先生，记住，我是一个淑女。”
'Remember, Mr. So-and-so, remember, I am a lady.'
你看你，在她面前说那种话
Look at you, talking that way in front of her.
-她会把所有的话都记在该死的日记里。  -写了又怎样？
- She puts it all in that damned diary. - So what if she does?
我只是说实话而已
I'm only telling the truth.
还没做完吗？
Haven't you finished yet?
没有
No.
哦，思想家
Oh. The thinker.
别管他
Leave him alone.
好吧，好吧。我是个蠢材，没用的东西
All right, all right. I'm a dunce, a hopeless case.
你不是没用
You're not hopeless.
你只是没有人帮你，就像爸爸帮助安妮和我一样
It's just that you haven't got anyone to help you like father helps Anne and me.
那么，要是我......要是我们能够帮......
Well, if I... Well, if we could help...
你看怎么样，彼得？你愿意和我们一起学习吗？
What about it, Peter? Would you like to study with us?
我们创建一所男女合校好吗？
Shall we make our school coeducational?
谢谢，当然愿意
Thanks. Yes.
弗兰克先生，你是个天使，完美的天使
Mr. Frank, you are an angel, an absolute angel.
为什么遇到那位之前，我没遇到你啊？
Why didn't I meet you before I met that one there?
我......想最好......
I... think it might be better...
彼得，你是不是要进你房间学习
if you went into your room, Peter, to work.
失陪了
Excuse me.
你要听弗兰克先生的。弗兰克先生受过高等教育
You listen to Mr. Frank. Mr. Frank is a highly educated man.
已经过8点了，他们都哪儿去了？
It's after 8:00. Where are they?
-至少其中一个人本应该来啊。  -他们会来的，别担心
- At least one of them should have come. - They'll come. Don't worry.
别这么说，我知道肯定是哪里不对劲了
Don't tell me. I know something's wrong.
你不四肢伸开躺在那占地方不好吗？
Isn't it bad enough around here without you sprawling all over the place?
要是你不这样一直抽烟，脾气就不会变得这么坏
If you didn't smoke all the time, you wouldn't be so bad-tempered.
-你看到我抽烟了？  -你已经把所有的烟抽光了
- Do you see me smoking? - You already smoked all the cigarettes?
就一包，米耶普只给我买了一包
One package. Miep only brought me one package.
你那是坏习惯，现在正是戒掉的好时候
It's a filthy habit, and this is a good time to break yourself of it.
-哦，闭嘴。  -你把所有的钱全抽光了
- Oh, stop it. - You're smoking up all our money!
能闭嘴吗！
Will you shut up!
你在盯着什么？
And what are you staring at?
我过去从来没有见过大人这样吵架
I never heard grown-ups quarrel like that before.
我还以为只有小孩才打架
I thought only children quarreled.
这不是吵架，是讨论
This isn't a quarrel. It's a discussion.
-我都没见过孩子这么粗鲁。  -我，粗鲁？
- And I never heard children so rude. - I, rude?
-是的。  -安妮，喝你的牛奶！
- Yes! - Anne, drink your milk.
你的麻烦是，你被惯坏了。你需要的是打屁股
The trouble with you is, you've been spoiled. You need a spanking.
记住，某某先生，我是一个淑女
Remember, Mr. So-and-so, that I am a lady.
你太让人恼火......
Mmm, you're the most aggravating...
为什么你不能像你的妹妹玛戈特那样优雅，安静一些？
Why aren't you nice and quiet like your sister Margot?
为什么你非得一直卖弄自己？
Why do you have to show off all the time?
让我给你一点忠告，年轻人――男人可不喜欢那样的女孩
Let me give you a little advice, young lady-- men don't like that in a girl.
你喜欢吗？一个男人喜欢听话的女孩
Do you know that? A man likes a girl who will listen to him once in a while.
-喜欢知道做饭，打扫的女孩。  -我宁可抹脖子
- A girl who loves to cook and clean-- - I'd cut my throat first!
我要张扬个性
I'd open my veins.
我要与众不同
I'm going to be remarkable.
我要去巴黎......
I'm going to Paris...
-巴黎？是的，是的。  -去学音乐和美术
- Paris? Yeah, yeah. - to study music and art.
我要做演员，作家或者舞蹈家
I'm going to be an actress, or a writer, or a dancer.
-看你做的事情。  -对不起
- Look what you did. - I'm so sorry.
你这个笨蛋！
You clumsy little fool!
-这是我爸爸留给我的大衣！  -对不起
- This is the coat my father gave me! - I'm so sorry.
你把大衣毁了。怎么这么不小心？你毁了大衣！
You ruined it. What do you care? Ruined it!
我要杀了你！我真想杀了你！
I could kill you! I could just kill you!
佩特罗内拉。宝贝，宝贝
Petronella. Liebchen, Liebchen.
佩特罗内拉
Petronella.
只是件大衣而已
It's only a coat.
安妮，你不可以那个样子
Anne, you must not behave in that way.
只是一个意外，谁都会出意外
It was an accident. Anyone can have an accident.
我不是那意思，我是说你顶嘴
I don't mean that. I mean the answering back.
你不可以顶嘴
You must not answer back.
他们都是客人
They're our guests.
玛戈特从来没有那样和客人争吵，不是吗？
You don't hear Margot getting into any arguments with them, do you?
向玛戈特学学
Try to be like Margot.
让他们象踩玛戈特那样踩我吗？不，谢谢了
And have them walk all over me the way they do her? No, thanks.
我不知道你到底怎么了，安妮
I don't know what happens to you, Anne.
要是当初我也象你对我说话那样，对我妈妈说话......
If I had ever talked to my mother as you talk to me--
一切都在变，妈妈
Things have changed, Mother.
大家都不那样了
People aren't like that anymore.
“是，妈妈。”，“不，妈妈”，“听你的，妈妈。”
"Yes, Mother." "No, Mother." "Anything you say, Mother."
我必须为自己努力争取
I've got to fight things out for myself.
-但是......    -争取自己应得的
- But...   - Make something of myself.
没必要去吵吵嚷嚷去争啊。玛戈特就不吵嚷
It isn't necessary to fight to do it. Margot doesn't fight.
玛戈特！我耳朵都灌满了
Margot! That's all I hear.
“为什么你不象玛戈特？”
"Why aren't you like Margot?"
她做什么都是对的，我做什么都是错的！
Everything she does is right, and everything I do is wrong!
你们都看不上我，你最看不上我！
You're all against me, and you worst of all!
我不知道这样过日子，还能挺多久
I don't know how we can go on living this way.
我一句都不能说安妮了，她和我吵来吵去
I can't say a word to Anne, she flies at me.
你了解安妮。不出半小时她就会连说带笑地出来
You know Anne. In a half hour she'll be out here laughing and joking.
并且，呃...
And, uh...
我告诉你爸爸这样根本不行――两家在一起
I told your father it wouldn't work-- two families.
不，不，他会问的
But no, no, he had to ask them.
嘘
Shh.
每次听到声音，我的心跳都要停了
Every time I hear that sound, my heart stops.
-是米耶普。  -爸爸！
- It's Miep. - father!
-啊？  -是米耶普
- Yes? - It's Miep.
这是你开的单子
Here's your list.
-是米耶普吗？  -是的
- Is it Miep? - Yes.
我终于能等到一些烟卷了
At last I'll have some cigarettes.
米耶普来了
Miep's here.
我都不好意思说我对那件大衣有多抱歉
I can't tell you how sorry I am about the coat.
没事了
Don't worry.
-你好，你好。  -米耶普
- Hello, hello. - Miep.
卡勒先生！
Mr. Kraler!
卡勒先生一露面，就阳光灿烂
When Mr. Kraler comes, the sun begins to shine.
-德克不得不离开了。  -德克是米耶普的未婚夫？
- Dirk has had to leave. - Dirk is Miep's fianc?
他得躲到乡下去，摆脱那些工人的电话
He had to go into hiding in the country to escape a labor call-up.
但是他让我给你们带来一台收音机
But he has let me have the radio for you.
他不该这样
He shouldn't have.
哦，太危险了
Oh, it was too dangerous.
看！
Look!
我们珍贵的收音机
Our blessed radio.
给了我们了解外面世界的眼睛和耳朵
It gives us our eyes and ears out into the world.
我们只听德国电台的好听音乐
We listen to the German station only for good music.
轴心国军队在西部沙漠......
The Axis forces in the Western desert...
为了希望，我们听着BBC
And we listen to the BBC for hope.
对我们陆空力量的持续攻击......
Ceaseless attacks by our land and air forces...
现在已经完全被遏制了
are now in full retreat.
英国军队在持续推进
The Eighth Army continues to advance.
好消息
That's good.
好吧，彼得。让我们听听他们会说纳粹什么
All right, Peter, now let's see what they have to say about the Nazis.
柏林
Berlin.
还要听吗？
Must we listen?
行了，彼得，够了
All right, Peter. That's enough.
环保警察，他们发现我们了
The Green Police. They've found us.
嗯
Hmm.
啊
Ah.
嘘
Huh.
Hmm.
这边走，达索尔先生
This way, Mr. Dussel.
-是卡勒，请开门。   -还有米耶普
- It is Kraler. Please open. - And Miep.
噢，保佑他们，他们来了
Oh, bless them. They are here.
-卡勒？  -还有米耶普。请开门
-Kraler? -And Miep,yes. Open, please.
-哦，昨晚来了一个访客。  -昨晚一个访客？
- Well, we had a visitor last night. - A visitor last night?
-是的，是的。  -一个窃贼
- Yes, yes. - A thief.
-那是个窃贼？  -你听到了？
- It was a thief? - Did you hear him?
-是的，我们听到了。  -他就在你们下面
- Yes, we heard him. - He was right under you.
-正下面的办公室里。  -我们不知道
- In the office right under here. - We did not know.
我们还以为是环保警察
We thought it was the Green Police.
-你能肯定吗，米耶普？  -当然，你们那时安静吗？
- Are you sure, Miep? - You were, of course, quiet?
我们没有动，甚至整晚都几乎没有呼吸
We didn't move. We hardly breathed all night.
-很好，很近啊。  -太近了
- That is good. It was close. - Too close.
他把桌子和所有的档案翻了个底朝天
He went through everything. The desk and the files.
桌子和所有的档案，并且也发现保险柜了，但是没能打开
The desk and the files. And he found the safe, but he could not get it open.
他在找我们从黑市弄的口粮供应卡
He was looking for our ration card supply from the Underground.
-有人知道。  -都在那个保险柜里
- Somebody knows. - They're in that safe.
他们还会回来。扔掉保险柜吧，从这儿弄出去。
They'll come back. Get rid of that safe. Get it out of here.
是的。门上贴个条子：
Yes. Put a sign on the door:
“窃贼，别回来了，保险柜已经没有了。”
"Burglars, do not come back. The safe is gone."
笑话而已
Jokes, yet.
-弗兰克先生，我得和你谈谈。  -好的
- Mr. Frank, I must talk to you. - Yes, of course.
或许是那台收音机。我们应该丢掉它
Maybe it's the radio. We should get rid of the radio.
扔到炉子里烧了吧。要是环保警察发现收音机......
Put it in the stove, burn it. If the Green Police found that radio...
或许还会发现她的日记。我们也要烧掉
And they'd find her diary. We'll burn that too.
我的日记不可以
Not my diary.
-我和日记共存亡。   -日记在哪？
- My diary goes, I go with it. - Where is it?
要是他们发现我们，他们同样会发现日记和收音机
If they find us, they might just as well find the diary, the radio.
有什么不同吗？
What'll be the difference?
-我来的时候，总是尽力带好消息。  -是的，我知道
- When I come, I try to bring good news. - Yes, I know.
发生了一件事，一个男人来找我
Something has happened. A man came to me.
他告诉我他有一个犹太朋友，一个牙医
He told me that he has a Jewish friend-- a dentist.
他求我帮他找个藏身地方，所以我来找你
He begged me, could I find him a hiding place? So I have come to you.
我知道很难说出口，象你们这样的状况......
I know it is a terrible thing to ask, living the way you are...
把他带来了吗？
but could you take him in?
-嗯，当然我们会收留。  -他叫让・达索尔
- Well, of course we will. - His name is Jan Dussel.
-达索尔，等等，我认识他。  -留下他很不错
- Dussel. Wait. I think I know him. - It's fine to have him.
但是，奥托，我们把他放在哪儿啊？哪里？
But, Otto, where are we going to put him? Where?
吃的这么少，还收留另外一个人......
There's so little food as it is, and to take in another person...
我们一人省一口就可以，范・戴恩先生
We can stretch the food a little, Mr. Van Daan.
-他可以用我的床。  -不用，谢谢你，彼得
- He can have my bed. - No, thank you, Peter.
玛戈特搬到我们这儿，他可以用她的床
Margot will move in here with us, and he can have her bed.
我把东西拿出来
I'll get my things out.
达索尔先生
Mr. Dussel.
别碰到头
Don't bump your head.
进来，达索尔先生
Come in, Mr. Dussel.
-这位是弗兰克先生。   -奥托・弗兰克先生？
- This is Mr. Frank. - Mr. Otto Frank?
是。把东西给我
Yes. Let me have your things, please.
谢谢，弗兰克先生。我把你交给他们了
Thank you, Mr. Frank. I leave you in good hands.
-达索尔先生？  -嗯？
- Mr. Dussel? - Hmm?
我得把大衣拿回去
I must return your coat.
我该怎么谢你啊？
What can I say to thank you?
卡勒先生，米耶普。他们是我们的生命线。没有他们，我们都活不了
Mr. Kraler, Miep, they're our lifeline. Without them, we couldn't live.
哦，你说的好像我们很崇高，并不是那样
Please,you make us seem very heroic. It isn't that at all.
我们只是不喜欢纳粹，不喜欢他们的所作所为......
We simply don't like the Nazis. We don't like their methods...
我知道。“没人告诉我们荷兰人该怎样对待该死的犹太人。”
I know. "Nobody's gonna tell us Dutchmen what to do with our damn Jews."
我们明早上来看看，他们会对你很好的
We will be up tomorrow to see that they are treating you right.
-再见。  -再见，卡勒先生
- Good-bye. - Good-bye, Mr. Kraler.
再见，米耶普
Good-bye, Miep.
欢迎，达索尔先生。   -谢谢
- Welcome, Mr. Dussel. - Thank you.
这是我妻子，埃蒂茨。范・戴恩先生太太
This is my wife, Edith. Mr. and Mrs. Van Daan.
他们的儿子，彼得。我的女儿玛戈特和安妮
Their son, Peter, my daughters Margot and Anne.
-安妮。   -你好
- Anne. - How do you do.
玛戈特。   -达索尔先生，请坐
- Margot. - Please, Mr. Dussel, sit down.
谢谢
Thank you.
我知道我在做梦
I'm dreaming, I know it.
奥托・弗兰克先生，这儿
Mr. Otto Frank, here.
那么你们不在瑞士？有人说你们逃到瑞士去了
You're not in Switzerland, then? Someone said that you escaped to Switzerland.
-你们一直在这儿？  -从七月份就一直在
- And you've been here all this time? - Ever since July.
卡勒先生没告诉你这里吃的东西不多吗？
Did Mr. Kraler warn you you won't get much to eat here?
你可以想象......我们七个人就三张配给卡
You can imagine... three ration cards among the seven of us.
现在是八个人了
Now you make eight.
范・戴尔先生，你还不知道外面在发生什么......
Mr. Van Daan, you don't realize what's happening outside...
你不该那样警告我
that you should warn me of a thing like that.
你还不知道在这里，阿姆斯特丹，在发生什么
You don't realize what's going on right here in Amsterdam.
每天成百上千的犹太人失踪
Every day, hundreds ofJews disappear.
他们包围街区，一户一户搜查
They surround a block, and they search house by house.
每天都有孩子们放学回到家，发现父母消失了
Every day children come home from school to find their parents gone.
成百成千的人被驱逐出境了
Hundreds are being deported.
你我都认识的人――豪恩斯坦一家，维塞尔一家。
People that you and I know--the Hallensteins, the Wessels.
噢，不
Oh, no.
你会收到通知书
You get your call-up notice
通知你某天某时到火车站
come to the station on such and such a day and hour.
只能带着随身的东西
Bring only what you can carry.
要是你不离开，他们就来把你拖走
If you don't go, they come and drag you from your home...
用船运到茅斯奥森――死亡营
and ship you off to Mauthausen-- the death camp.
我们不知道情况会变得这么糟
We didn't know that things had got so much worse.
原谅我说那些
Forgive me for speaking so.
你认识德・沃瑞斯一家嘛？
Do you know the de Vries?
他们走了
They're gone.
珊妮和我同班
Sanne and I are in the same class.
珊妮是我最好的――最好的朋友
Sanne is my best-- my best friend.
她放学回家发现父母不见了
She returned home from school to find her parents gone.
她自己呆了两天，来人就把她带走了
She was alone for two days, and then they came and took her away.
走了？
Gone?
和所有其他人
With all the others.
噢，不
Oh, no.
还有叫梅耶伯格的，就住在我们附近......
Some people named Meyerberg, they lived near us...
我想我们晚些时候在谈这些吧，范・戴恩太太
I think we should put this off until later, Mrs. Van Daan.
我肯定达索尔先生需要安顿一下了
I'm sure Mr. Dussel would like to get settled now.
安妮，把达索尔先生带到他的房间好吗？
Annele, would you like to take Mr. Dussel to his room?
请跟我来，达索尔先生
If you'll come with me, Mr. Dussel.
哦，不胜感激
Uh, forgive me if I haven't expressed my gratitude.
这是对我多大的打击啊
This has been such a shock to me.
我一直认为自己是荷兰人
I always thought of myself as Dutch.
我生在荷兰
I was born in Holland.
我爸爸生在荷兰，我爷爷也生在荷兰
My father was born in Holland, and my grandfather.
过了这么多年......
And now after all these years...
失陪了
If you will excuse me.
和卡勒先生告诉我们的太不一样了
It's so different from what Mr. Kraler tells us.
卡勒先生说情况在改善
Mr. Kraler says that things are improving.
我宁愿是卡勒先生说的那样
I like it better the way Kraler tells it.
晚上好，巴比勒
Good night, Bubele.
-该说晚安了。   -晚安，妈妈
- Say good night. - Good night, Mother.
-晚安，弗兰克先生。   -晚安
- Good night, Mr. Frank. - Good night.
晚安
Good night.
你有孩子吗，达索尔先生？
Do you have any children, Mr. Dussel?
没有，我没结婚
No, I never married.
-你没有亲人吗？  - 一个也没有
- Have you no family at all? - No one.
太可怕了，你一定相当孤独
How dreadful. You must be terribly lonely.
嗯，我已经习惯了
Mm. I'm used to it.
我肯定不会习惯
I don't think I could get used to it.
-你有宠物吗？一只猫或者一条狗？  -没有
- Didn't you have a pet? A cat or a dog? - No.
不，不。我对带毛动物过敏
No, no. I have an allergy to fur-bearing animals.
-会让我哮喘。  -哦，天啊
- Gives me asthma. - Oh, dear.
-怎么了？   -彼得有只猫
- What? - Peter has a cat.
-他有？他有只猫在这儿？  -是的
- He has? He has it here? - Yes.
我们很少见到，彼得一直在自己房间养它
We hardly ever see it. He keeps it in his room all the time.
我相信会好的
I'm sure it will be all right.
啊哈，那么，希望如此吧
Mm-hmm. Well, I hope so.
我希望不会太打扰你，达索尔先生
I hope I'm not going to be too much of a bother to you, Mr. Dussel.
不会的
No.
我好像能让每个人都生气
I seem to be able to get everyone's back up.
哦，我总是和孩子们相处很好
Oh, I always get along very well with young people.
我的病人都把他们的孩子带来......
My patients all bring their children to me...
因为他们知道我和孩子们合得来
because they know I get along well with them.
所以不必担心
So don't you worry about that.
谢谢，达索尔先生
Thank you, Mr. Dussel.
晚安，我马上回来
Good night. I'll be back.
晚安，达索尔先生
Good night, Mr. Dussel.
当心
Careful.
珊妮
Sanne.
珊妮？
Sanne?
珊妮
Sanne.
停！
Halt!
救救我！救救我！不，不！
Save me! Save me! No, no!
-不！不，不要碰我！  -住手。住手
- Oh! No, don't take me! - Stop it. Stop it.
-救救我。   -安静，亲爱的
-Save me. -Hush, darling.
安静。没事了。没事了
Hush. It's all right. It's all right.
达索尔先生，请打开灯。只是个梦
Please, Mr. Dussel, turn on the light. It was just a dream.
你在这里，很安全。知道吗？
You're here, safe. You see?
这孩子一定有什么事，那么大声叫
Something must be done with that child, yelling like that.
谁知道什么人会在街上。她危及到我们生命了
Who knows who might be in the street. She's endangering all our lives.
达索尔先生，毕竟安妮不是训练有素的前线士兵
Mr. Dussel, after all, Anne is not exactly a trained, frontline soldier.
达索尔先生，请回去睡觉吧
Please, Mr. Dussel, go back to bed.
过一两分钟她就会好，对吗，安妮？
She'll be herself in a minute or two. Won't you, Anne?
回去睡觉
Go back to bed.
打扰下，我要去厕所，唯一安静的地方
Excuse me. I'm going to the W.C., the one room where there's peace.
现在回去睡觉
Go back to bed now.
要点水吗？
Would you like some water?
是个恶梦吗？
Was it a very bad dream?
也许你能告诉我
Perhaps if you told me.
-我宁可不说。  -好好睡觉吧
- I'd rather not talk about it. - Try to sleep then.
-我就坐在你旁边。  -不用的
- I'll sit right here beside you. - You don't have to.
我真的非常想陪你
But I'd like to stay with you very much. Really.
真的不用了
I'd rather you didn't.
晚安...
Good night...
没事吧？什么也不要吗？
You'll be all right? There's nothing that you want?
能让爸爸过来吗？
Will you please ask father to come?
当然，安妮宝贝
Yes, of course, Anne dear.
她叫你
She asks for you.
-埃蒂茨。   -去吧，奥托
- Edith. - Go to her, Otto.
她在吓得发抖
She's still trembling with fear.
她不需要我
She wants nothing of me.
我弯腰去亲她，她躲开了
She pulled away when I leaned down to kiss her.
环保警察破门而入，抓住我......
The Green Police broke down a door and grabbed me...
要把我象珊妮一样拖走
and tried to drag me out the way they did Sanne.
只是一个年龄阶段而已
It's just a phase.
所有的女孩在这个阶段都要爸爸
All girls turn to their fathers at this age.
把所有的爱给爸爸
They give all their love to their fathers.
你不该这样，不该排斥我
You weren't like this. You didn't shut me out.
那么......
So...
那么，要不要我给你读一会书？
now, do you want me to read to you for a while?
不。陪我坐一会就行
No.Just sit with me for a minute.
我很讨厌吗？你认为是不是外面的人都听到了？
Was I awful? Do you think anyone outside could've heard me?
不。现在安静地躺着。就这样
No. Now lie down quietly. So, like this.
现在使劲睡着吧
Now try to sleep.
我是个胆小鬼。我对自己失望极了
I'm a terrible coward. I'm so disappointed in myself.
我想我真的已经长大了......
I think I'm really grown up...
然后发生事情，我却象小孩一样跑到你身边
and then something happens and I run to you like a baby.
我爱你，爸爸。除了你，我谁也不爱
I love you, father. I don't love anyone but you.
安妮。安妮。
Annele. Annele.
真的，你是我唯一爱的
It's true. You're the only one I love.
我已经想很长时间了
I've been thinking about it for a long time.
很好，能告诉我你爱我 ，那很好......
It's fine-- It's fine to have you tell me that you love me...
但是，要是你能告诉我你也爱你妈妈，我会更高兴
but I'd be much happier if you said that you loved your mother as well.
她太需要你的帮助了
She needs your help so much.
-那时你的爱。  -我们没有共同语言
- Your love. - We have nothing in common.
她不理解我
She doesn't understand me.
每当我想说说对生命的看法，她就问我是不是便秘
Whenever I try to explain my views on life, she asks me if I'm constipated.
刚才你太伤她心了。她在哭。在那里哭呢
You hurt her very much just now. She's crying. She's in there crying.
噢，爸爸，我是不是很可怕？
Oh, father, I was horrible, wasn't I?
我怎么了？告诉我
What's the matter with me? Tell me.
不要说这是要经历的阶段。帮帮我
Don't say it's just a phase. Help me.
安妮，父母对孩子能做的太少啊
There's so little we parents can do to help our children, Anne.
我们只是尽力作个好榜样，指出一条路
We can only try to set a good example. Point the way.
其余的都得靠你自己
The rest you must do yourself.
我在努力，真的
I'm trying. Really, I am.
每天晚上我都在反省我过去做过的所有错事
Every night I think back over all the things I did that day that were wrong.
就像把湿拖把放到范・戴恩太太床上
Like putting the wet mop in Mrs. Van Daan's bed.
现在又放到妈妈那里
And now this with Mother.
我对自己说：“那是错误的。”
I say to myself, "That was wrong."
并且下决心再也不那么做了。再也不
And I make up my mind I'm never going to do that again. Never.
我也许会做更坏的事情，但是绝不会做那件事
I may do something worse, but I'll never do that again.
我也有好的地方，爸爸
I have a nicer side, father.
但是我害怕表现出来
But I'm scared to show it.
我怕大家会嘲笑我
I'm afraid people will laugh at me.
所以坏安妮来到外面......
So the mean Anne comes to the outside...
好安妮呆在里面......
and the good Anne stays in the inside.
我也在一直努力改变......
And I keep on trying to switch them around...
让好安妮在外面，把坏安妮留在里面
and have the good Anne outside and the bad Anne inside.
那就是我要做的......
It would be what I'd like to be...
或许......要是......
and might be... if only...
她睡着了
She's asleep.
1942年10月29日，星期四
Thursday, the 29th of October, 1942.
达索尔先生和我昨天大吵了一架
Mr. Dussel and I had a great battle yesterday.
是的，达索尔先生
Yes, Mr. Dussel.
在达索尔先生看来，没有，我在说一遍，我就没有任何可取之处
According to him, nothing, I repeat, nothing is right about me.
当他针对我的时候，我就想......
While he was going on at me, I thought...
总有一天，我要好好扇你.....
"Someday, I'm going to give you such a smack...
把你扇到棚顶去
that you'll fly right up to the ceiling. '"
为什么所有大人都认为他知道怎样养大孩子？
Why is it that every grown-up thinks he knows the way to bring up children?
尤其是那些没有孩子的大人
Particularly the grown-ups that haven't any.
1942年11月9日，星期一
Monday, the ninth of November, 1942.
好消息。盟国在非洲登路了
Wonderful news. The Allies have landed in Africa.
丘吉尔在伦敦BBC发表讲话
Churchill spoke on the bbC from London.
他们常常给予别人的
Which they have so often meted out to others.
这不是结束
Ah, this is not the end.
这甚至不是结束的开始
No, it is not even the beginning of the end.
但这毕竟是开始的结束
But it is, perhaps, the end of the beginning.
空袭越来越严重
The air raids are getting worse.
英国飞机日夜飞往德国
The British planes come over day and night on their way to Germany.
太多了，太多了
It's too much. Just too much.
要是他们炸到这所房子，我们该怎么办啊？
Suppose they hit this house? What will we do?
我们不能到街上去。我们该怎么办啊？
We can't go out in the street. What will we do?
要是他们炸到这所房子，你的烦恼就解决了
If they hit this house, your worries will be over.
那个噪音――爆炸声――他们击中英国飞机了
That noise--that big explosion--they hit one of the English planes.
-正好落在这个街区。  -彼得
- It fell right in this block. - Peter!
彼得！
Peter!
-离这儿很远。  -不要紧张
-It's far away from here. - Don't be nervous.
看着吧。嗨，范・戴恩太太，对你来说，这就像音乐吧
Just look at them. Why, Mrs. Van Daan, this should be music to your ears.
-音乐？  -当然
- Music?  - Of course.
英国派来的飞机越多......
The more planes the British send over...
战争就结束的越快，我们也就能越快从这出去回家
the sooner the war will be over, the sooner we'll be out of here and home.
我都不相信战争会结束
I don't believe it'll ever be over.
你知道我现在需要的吗？一杯茶
You know what I'd like right now? A cup of tea.
哦，是的，请
Oh, yes, please.
你不能喝早餐的茶
You can't have tea then for breakfast.
要是现在喝茶，明天你就没有了
If you have tea now, you won't have any tomorrow.
-我不在乎。  -我也不在乎
- I don't care. - Neither do I.
我也是
Me, too, please.
那么你呢，达索尔先生？是现在喝你的茶还是明天早晨？
How about you, Mr. Dussel? Would you like your tea now or tomorrow morning?
-明天早晨。  -肯定吗？
- Tomorrow morning. - Sure?
肯定
Sure.
我现在喝我那份茶
I'll take mine now.
探照灯！
The skylight!
埃蒂茨，过来！
Edith, come!
彼得！彼得！彼得！彼得！
Peter! Peter! Peter! Peter!
彼得！
Peter!
“赞美你，我主上帝......”
"Praised be Thou, O Lord our God...
“万物之主，用戒律使我们圣洁......”
"ruler of the universe who has sanctified us with Thy commandments...
“吩咐我们点燃光明节之灯。”
"and bidden us kindle the Hanukkah lights.
“赞美你，我主上帝，万物之主......”
"Praise be Thou, O Lord our God, ruler of the universe...
“使我们残年的父亲得到奇异的庇护。”
"who has wrought wondrous deliverances for our fathers in days of old.
“赞美你，我主上帝，万物之主......”
"Praise be Thou, O Lord our God, ruler of the universe...
“赐予我们生命，食物，给我们带来这快乐的季节。”
"that Thou has given us life, sustenance and brought us to this happy season.
-“阿门。”   -阿门
- Amen." - Amen.
1942年12月7日，星期一
Monday, the seventh of December, 1942.
今年光明节来的很早
The Hanukkah holiday came early this year.
“我们点燃光明节之灯......
"We kindle this Hanukkah light...
"赞美伟大美好的事迹......
"to celebrate the great and wonderful deeds...
“用上帝赐予心中的热忱工作......
"wrought through the zeal with which God filled the hearts...
"在2000年前的马卡比书中
"of the heroic Maccabees 2,000 years ago.
"与冷漠，暴虐和压迫而战......
"They fought against indifference, against tyranny and oppression...
"为我们修复了庙宇
"and they restored our temple to us.
愿这些灯提醒我们要永远遵从上帝.....
"May these lights remind us that we should ever look to God...
"我们得到帮助之地
"whence cometh our help.
"-阿门。”  -阿门
- Amen." -Amen.
"我要向山举目。我的帮助从何而来
"I lift up mine eyes unto the mountains from whence cometh my help.
"我的帮助从造天地的上帝而来
"My help cometh from the Lord who made heaven and Earth.
"他必不叫你的脚摇动
"He will not suffer thy foot to be moved.
保护你的必不打盹
"He that keepeth thee will not slumber.
“保护以色列的，也不打盹，也不睡觉
"He that keepeth Israel doth neither slumber nor sleep.
“保护你的是上帝。上帝在你的右边荫庇你
"The Lord is thy keeper. The Lord is thy shade upon thy right hand.
上帝要保护你，免受一切的灾害。他要保护你的性命
"The Lord shall keep thee from all evil. He shall keep thy soul.
“你出你入上帝要保护你......
"The Lord shall guard thy going out and thy coming in...
“从今时直到永远
"from this time forth and forevermore.
"-阿门。”  -阿门
- Amen." - Amen.
-阿门。  -可以给我帽子吗？
- Amen. - May I have the hats, please?
谢谢
Thank you.
-很好，很好。   -太感动了
- Very nice. Very nice. - That was very moving.
-坐下。   -坐下
- Sit down. - Sit down.
-你要去哪儿？  -这里有很多的歌声和礼物
- Where are you going? - There's lots more. Songs and presents.
-礼物？  -很不幸，今年可没有
- Presents? - Not this year, unfortunately.
但是光明节每个人都会送礼物。人人都会
But always on Hanukkah everyone gives presents. Everyone.
-是的。   -就像我们的圣尼古拉节一样
- That's right. - Like our Saint Nicholas day.
-圣尼古拉节。  -和圣尼古拉节不一样
- Saint Nicholas day. - No, not like Saint Nicholas day.
你算是什么犹太人，竟然不知道光明节？
What kind of a Jew are you that you don't know Hanukkah?
我印象深刻的是蜡烛。先点一支，就像今晚这样
I remember particularly the candles. First one, as we have tonight.
然后第二夜点燃两支。再一夜是三支
Then the second night, you light two candles. The next night, three.
以此类推，一直到八支蜡烛点燃
And so on, until there are eight candles burning.
当点燃八支蜡烛的时候，相当美丽啊
When there are eight candles, it's truly beautiful.
我记忆最深刻的是我们得到的礼物
What I remember best are the presents we used to get.
得到八天礼物。啊，一天比一天的好
Eight days of presents, and, well, each day they got better and better.
我们都在这里，都活着。这个礼物就足够了
We're all here... alive. That's present enough.
-不，不是。我有一些东西。  -是什么？
- No, it isn't. I've got something. - What is it?
-干杯。   -干杯
- L 'Chaim. - L 'Chaim.
-礼物。   真正的礼物？
- Presents. - Real presents?
-她自己做的。   -看这个
- She made it herself. - Look at that.
-这不是节日吗？不该多彩一些吗？  -噢，真漂亮
- Isn't it festive? Isn't it gay? - Oh, that's beautiful.
-给玛戈特。  -啊
- For Margot. - Ah.
大声读
Read it out loud.
“你从来不发脾气。
"You have never lost your temper.
“我恐怕你永远不会
"You never will, I fear.
你太好了。但是要是可以的话，把你的纵横字谜放在这里。”
You are so good, but if you should, put all your cross words here."
啊
Aww.
让我们看看是什么
Let's see what it is.
是一本崭新的字谜书
It's a new crossword puzzle book.
是你做过的。我把答案擦掉了......
It's one you've done, but I rubbed it all out...
要是你等到忘记了，就可以重做一遍
and if you wait a little and forget, you can do it again.
-聪明，聪明。   -谢谢
- Clever, clever. - Thank you.
-给范・戴恩太太。  -啊哈
- For Mrs. Van Daan. - Ah-hah.
我真难过。我没有东西给大家
I feel terrible. I don't have a thing for anybody.
是洗发香波
It's hair shampoo.
我把肥皂的边边角角用我上次的洗漱用水化在一起
I took odds and ends of soap and mixed them with the last of my toilet water.
-噢，谢谢，安妮。  -太好了
- Oh, thank you, Anneke. - That was nice.
我要为所有人写首诗，但是我没有时间
I wanted to write a poem for all of them, but I didn't have time.
没关系，安妮
That's all right, Anne.
你的，范・戴恩先生，绝对是有用的东西
Yours, Mr. Van Daan, is really something.
-你最想要的东西。  -嗯
- Something you want more than anything. - Hmm.
-香烟！  -看
- Cigarettes! - Look at that.
-香烟。  -两支
- Cigarettes. - Two of them.
爸爸在他的大衣里兜发现了一些旧烟叶......
father found some old pipe tobacco in the pocket lining of his coat...
我们就卷出来了-不如说是爸爸卷的
and we made them-- rather, father did.
看啊
Look at that.
点上！快点上！
Light it! Go on and light it!
是烟叶，真的是
It's tobacco. Really, it is.
里面有一点绒毛，但是不多
There's a little fluff in it, but not much.
-点着了！  -看他！
- It works! -Look at him.
谢谢你，安妮。谢谢
Thank you, Anne. Thank you.
范・戴恩先生！
Mr. Van Daan!
爸爸的。光明节的问候
For Mother. Hanukkah greeting.
这里有个我要支付的借据
"Here's an I.O.U. that I promise to pay.
“做十个小时你吩咐我做的任何事情
"Ten hours of doing... whatever you say.
签名，安妮・弗兰克。”
Signed, Anne Frank."
十个小时任何要你做的事情？
Ten hours of doing what you're told?
-任何要你做的事情？  -对
- Anything you're told? - That's right.
你不会要把它卖了吧，弗兰克太太，是吗？
You wouldn't want to sell that, Mrs. Frank, would you?
绝不会。这是我得到的最珍贵的礼物
Never. This is the most precious gift I've ever had.
-给爸爸。  -我没想到还能得到礼物
- For father. - I wasn't supposed to have a present.
-看。   -是条围巾
- Look at that. - It's a muffler.
-哦，知道。   -象领带那样围在脖子上
-Oh, I know. -To wear around your neck like an ascot.
我每天晚上在黑暗中织的。我恐怕在黑暗中会更好看
I knitted it in the dark each night. I'm afraid it looks better in the dark.
真漂亮。谢谢，安妮。谢谢
It's fine. Thank you, Annele. Thank you.
-太漂亮了。  -好可爱，不是吗？谢谢，安妮
- Isn't it beautiful. - Lovely, huh? Thank you, Anne.
-给毛刺的。  -他一定会喜欢
- For Mouschi. -He'll like it.
这是给你的。你自己的，来自呱呱小姐
And this is for you. Yourself. From Miss Quack-Quack.
快，打开
Go on. Open it.
不想打开吗？
Aren't you going to open it?
-给我们看看是什么。  -是个安全剃须刀
-Show us what it is. - It's a safety razor.
不是新的。米耶普给我弄的二手货。你的确需要有个剃须刀
It's not new. Miep got it for me second-hand. But you do need a razor.
-用来做什么？  -看他的上唇。看到没有？
- What for? - Look at his upper lip. See?
他要刮掉吗？
He wants to get rid of that?
上面涂些牛奶，让你的猫舔掉
Put some milk on it and let the cat lick it off.
你认为很可笑，是吗？
You think you're funny, don't you?
看，他都等不及了。他现在就要去试试
Look, he can't wait. He's going in to try it now.
我要把礼物给毛刺
I'm going to give Mouschi his present.
-毛刺，毛刺，毛刺。  -够了
- Mouschi, Mouschi, Mouschi. - Enough.
最后，却不是最少，给我的室友，达索尔先生
And last, but never least, my roommate, Mr. Dussel.
有东西给我？
Something for me?
-胶囊。  -是耳塞，塞到你的耳朵里......
- Capsules. - They're earplugs to put in your ears...
那样晚上我折腾的时候，你就听不见了
so you won't hear me when I thrash around at night.
我自己做的，试一下，看能不能听到我
I made them myself. Try them. See if you can hear me.
等我塞进去――这样吗？你是这意思吗？
Wait, I'll put-- Like that? Is that what you mean?
-准备好了吗？  -什么？
- Are you ready? - What?
-准备好了吗？  -好使了
- Are you ready? - They work.
出不来了。出不来了
They went in. They went in.
他拿不出来了。你怎么了？拿出来
He can't get 'em out. What's the matter with you? Get 'em out.
把耳塞拿出来
Take 'em out.
拿出来了
I got 'em.
谢谢你
Thank you.
现在让我们唱一首歌吧，爸爸
And now let's sing the song, father.
等等，你就要听到光明节颂歌了，达索尔先生
Wait till you hear the Hanukkah song, Mr. Dussel.
安妮，我们今晚不该唱歌
Annele, we shouldn't sing the song tonight.
你看，达索尔先生，那是一首喜悦，欢乐之歌
You see, Mr. Dussel, it's a song of jubilation and of rejoicing.
人啊，太真容易对那种事情兴致勃勃了
One is apt to become just a little too enthusiastic about it.
求你，爸爸，让我们唱颂歌吧。我保证不喊
Please, let's sing the song, father. I promise not to shout.
-好吧，不过要小声，安妮。  -哦！
- Very well, but quietly, Anne. - Oh!
哦！我告诉过你不要带猫过来
Oh! I told you not to come in here with that cat.
出去
Get out of here.
你怎么了？难道你没有感觉吗？
What's the matter with you? Haven't you any sense?
-把猫弄出去。  -猫？
- Get that cat out of here. - Cat?
听着，把它弄出去！
You heard me. Get it out of here!
我没有猫
I have no cat.
达索尔先生！
Mr. Dussel!
不必是猫本身
It doesn't have to be the cat.
仅仅猫身上的毛就足够了
Just the hairs on his clothing from the cat is enough.
-当他进来的时候......  -不要再烦人了
- When he comes in the room...  - You won't be bothered anymore.
-我们必须摆脱它。  -最后，你听我说
- We're getting rid of it. - At last, you listen to me.
我并不是替你说话。都是你自己认为的，都是
I'm not doing it for you. That's all in your mind. All of it.
我那么做是因为，看到那只猫吃掉所有我们的食物，我很恼火
I'm doing it because I'm sick of seeing that cat eat all our food.
不对。我只是喂它残渣剩饭
That's not true. I only give him scraps.
得了。它天天在胖
Don't tell me. He gets fatter every day.
该死的猫看起来比我们过的都好。今晚让它滚出去
Damn cat looks better than any of us. Out he goes tonight.
-不！  -范・戴恩先生，你不能那么做
- No! - Mr. Van Daan, you can't do that.
那是彼得的猫。彼得爱他的猫
That's Peter's cat. Peter loves that cat.
安妮
Anne.
-要是他走，我也走。  -走，走
- If he goes, I go. - Go. Go.
他不会走，猫也不用走。你怎么了？
He's not going, and the cat's not going. What's the matter with you?
光明节。光明节，来，安妮，唱歌
It's Hanukkah. It's Hanukkah. Please, Anne, sing.
安妮
Annele.
我想我们应该先把蜡烛吹灭
I think we should first blow out the candles.
那样明晚还会有东西了
Then we'll have something for tomorrow night.
爸爸，你应该让蜡烛自己点完
father, you're supposed to let it burn itself out.
我肯定上帝会理解我们的窘迫的
I'm sure that God understands shortages.
赞美我主，供养我们......
Praise be Thou, O Lord our God, who has sustained us...
允许我们欢庆这快乐的节日
and permitted us to celebrate this joyous festival.
-阿门。  -阿门
- Amen. -Amen.
-我想他们走了。 -他们发现我们了
- I think they've gone. - They found us.
要是发现了，他们现在就已经上来了
If they had, they would be up here by now.
我知道那一定是环保警察。他们去找帮手了
I know it was the Green Police. They've gone to get help.
或许是盖世太保，在找文件
It may be the Gestapo, looking for papers.
或者是另一个窃贼在找钱
Or another thief looking for money.
我下去
I'm going down.
-他们可能还在那儿。  -安妮，今天是星期六
- They may still be there. - Annele, this is Saturday.
我们没办法知道下面发生什么了......
We have no way of knowing what has happened down there...
等米耶普和卡勒先生来了才能知道
until Miep and Mr. Kraler come.
我们不能活在茫然未知中。现在，让我去看看
We cannot live with this uncertainty. Now, please. Please.
拿我们的钱来。他们说你可以买通他们。这么多钱买一条命不少了
Get our money. They say you can buy them off. So much a head.
-快，上楼拿钱。  -安静
- Quick, go upstairs and get the money. - Keep still.
你想被拖到集中营去吗？
You wanna be dragged off to a concentration camp?
你想站在这，直到他们来带走你吗？
You gonna stand there until they come up here and get you?
安静行不？
Will you keep still!
有人来了，让爸爸回来
Someone go and make father come back.
-你还没做够吗？  -不要这样，范・戴恩先生
- Haven't you done enough? - Please, Mr. Van Daan.
-安妮。  -嘘
- Anne! - Shh.
我要向山举目。我的帮助从何而来
I lift up mine eyes unto the mountains from whence cometh my help.
我的帮助从造天地的上帝而来
My help cometh from the Lord who made heaven and Earth.
保护你的必不打盹
He that keepeth thee will not slumber.
保护以色列的，也不打盹，也不睡觉
He that keepeth Israel doth neither slumber nor sleep.
保护你的是上帝。上帝的荫庇来自......
The Lord is thy keeper. The Lord is thy shade from--
不
No.
-我最好去看看，确定一下。  -呀
- I better go and look and make sure. - Ja.
祈求我主保佑你远离邪恶
Pray that the Lord shall keep thee from all evil.
-保佑你的灵魂。  -请聆听我的祈祷，哦，以色列
- He shall keep thy soul. - Hear me, O Israel.
我主将荫庇你的出入
The Lord shall guard thy going out and thy coming in.
他带着打字机匆忙跑了......
He took the typewriter and ran away in such a hurry...
他没关大门――还敞着呢
he didn't stop to shut the street door-- it was swinging wide open.
一个更夫过来了
A watchman was passing.
看，工具
Look. Tools.
呀
Ja.
妙-妙-妙. 妙-妙-妙，妙，妙
Meetz-meetz-meetz. Meetz-meetz-meetz. Meow, meow.
他们失窃了。他听到我来就出去了
They had a burglary. He got out as he heard me coming.
妙-妙，妙-妙
Meetz-meetz，Meetz-meetz.
我要锁上门去报告
I will lock the door and report it.
他们走了。他们把门锁上了
They've gone. They've locked the door.
感谢上帝他们走了
Thank God they've gone.
我宁愿他们带走我们，而不继续忍受这个可怕的痛苦
I'd just as soon they'd take us than to continue with this terrible agony.
-我受不了了。  -没事了，安妮
- I can't stand it. - It's all right, Annele.
-危险过去了。  -谁说危险过去了？
- The danger has passed. - Who says the danger is passed?
你没意识到我们比过去更危险了吗？
Don't you realize that we're in greater danger than ever?
哦，达索尔先生，能安静一下吗？
Please, Mr. Dussel, will you keep still.
因为这个笨蛋，人们现在知道我们在这里了
Thanks to this clumsy fool, someone now knows we're up here.
-人们知道我们藏在这里。  -是个窃贼
- Someone knows we're up here hiding. - It's a thief.
你想那个窃贼会不会去环保警察那里报告......
You think the thief is going to go to the Green Police and say...
“我某个夜里在一个地方偷东西，听到我头上有声音”?
"I was robbing a place the other night, and I heard a noise above my head"?
-你认为一个窃贼会那么做吗？  -会的
- You think a thief is going to do that? - Yes, he will.
-你疯了。  -总有一天窃贼会被抓住
- You're crazy. - Someday the thief will be caught.
他会和盖世太保做笔交易
He'll make a bargain with the Gestapo.
他会和盖世太保说：“要是你放了我......
He'll say to the Gestapo, "If you let me off...
我会告诉你那些犹太人藏在哪里。”
I'll show you where some Jews are hiding."
-我就这么认为。  -噢！
- That's what I think. - Oy!
-他说的对。  -哦，妈妈，让我们离开这里吧
- He's right. - Oh, Mother, let's get out of here.
-我们不能住在这里了。  -求你，让我们走
- We can't stay here now. - Please, let's go.
走？去哪儿？
Go? Where?
是啊，去哪儿？
Yes, where?
我们都失去信心了吗？
Have we lost all faith?
所有的勇气？
All courage?
几个月前，我们认为他们会来抓我们，不是吗？
A few moments ago, we thought they had come for us, didn't we?
我们认为都完了。你看，并没有完，我们还活着。我们很安全
We thought it was the end. Well, it was not the end. We are alive. We are safe.
感谢我主，你无边的仁慈......
We thank Thee, O Lord, our God, that in Thy infinite mercy...
再次赐予我们安适
Thou hast again seen fit to spare us.
-阿门。  -阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
安妮
Annele.
颂歌，啊？
The song, hmm?
唱颂歌怎么样？
How about the song?
光明节快乐
Happy Hanukkah.
1944年1月1日，星期六
Saturday, the first of January, 1944.
又一个新年到来了......
Another new year has begun...
我们发觉我们还藏在这里
and we find ourselves still in our hiding place.
我们藏在这里已经一年五个月零二十五天了
We have been here now for one year, five months and 25 days.
其中一个成员离开了
One of our family has left us.
毛刺跑掉了
Mouschi ran away.
我们都消瘦了
We're all a little thinner.
范・戴恩先生的各种议论还是象过去一样猛烈
The Van Daans'discussions are as violent as ever.
妈妈仍然不理解我，不过我也一样不理解她
Mother still doesn't understand me, but then, I don't understand her either.
然而，有一个很大的变化，我自己的变化
There is one great change, however. A change in myself.
我曾经在哪里读到过，象我这个年龄的女孩，总是感觉......
I read somewhere that girls of my age don't feel quite certain of themselves...
在内心深处变得不安分......
that they become quiet within...
并且开始想着在身体中发生的奇迹
and begin to think of the miracle that is taking place in their bodies.
我想我身上发生的一切都太美妙了
I think that what is happening to me is so wonderful.
不仅仅是外表能看到的，还有内在发生的一切
Not only what can be seen, but what is taking place inside.
每次变化发生的时候，我就拥有了一个甜蜜的秘密......
Each time it has happened, I feel I have a sweet secret...
我渴望再次感觉到秘密的时刻
and I long for the time when I shall feel that secret within me again.
安妮，彼得
Annele. Peter.
一个惊喜，卡勒先生和米耶普来了
A wonderful surprise. Mr. Kraler and Miep are here.
哦，谢谢。你们可以不必来的
Oh, thank you. You shouldn't have come.
你们至少该给你们自己留一天
You should have at least one day to yourselves.
别那么说。见到他们太好了
Don't say that. It's so wonderful to see them.
-那是什么？那是什么？  -卡勒先生
- What is it? What is it? - Mr. Kraler.
-新年快乐，达索尔先生。  -新年快乐
- Happy New Year, Mr. Dussel. - Happy New Year.
-你好吗，玛戈特，感觉好点了吧？  -我很好
- How are you, Margot? Feeling better? - I'm all right.
我们用各种药把她填满了
We filled her full of every kind of pill...
所以她不咳嗽弄出噪音了
so she won't cough and make a noise.
看米耶普给我们带来什么了。 一只蛋糕
Look what Miep has brought us. A cake.
嗯
Mmm.
-蛋糕。  -是啊
- Cake. - Well.
-我拿些盘子。  -谢谢你，米耶普
- I'll get some plates. - Thank you, Miepia.
你肯定把好几个星期定量的糖用了
You must have used all of your sugar rations for weeks.
多漂亮啊，不是吗？
It's beautiful, isn't it?
从我上次见到蛋糕，都好几个世纪了
It's ages since I've even seen a cake.
从去年你买了一个以后就没见过，记得吗？
Not since you brought the one last year, remember?
上面写着“1943年和平”......
It had "Peace in 1943" written on...
“1944年和平”
"Peace in 1944."
-你知道和平一定会到来。  -给你
- Peace has to come sometime, you know. - Here you are.
--你知道和平一定会到来。  -给你
那么，我们一共几个人？
Now, how many of us are there?
-不用算我们，谢谢。  -哦，得算
- None for me, thank you. - Oh, you must.
来吧，米耶普
Please, Miep.
好。还有一，二，三...我们七个人
Good. That leaves one, two, three... seven of us.
八个。和往常一样
Eight. The same as it always is.
我没算玛戈特。我担保玛戈特一点也不会吃
I left Margot out. I take it for granted Margot won't eat any.
-为什么她不吃啊？  -我想吃点对她没有坏处
- Why wouldn't she? - I think it won't harm her.
好吧，好吧。我只是不想让她再咳嗽
All right, all right. I just didn't want her to start coughing again.
弗兰克太太，请切蛋糕吧
And, please, Mrs. Frank should cut the cake.
-你什么意思？  -啊，弗兰克太太分东西更好
- What do you mean? - Well, Mrs. Frank divides things better.
-你到底要说什么?  -得了，我们在浪费时间
-Just what are you trying to say? - Forget it. We're wasting time.
不，不。我难道是一直分配不公吗？
No, no. Don't I always give everybody exactly the same?
-我不公吗？  -得了，卡里
- Don't I? - Forget it, Kerli.
不，我要解释。我不公吗？
No, I want an answer. Don't I?
不，不，不。你分配的很公平
Yes. Yes, yes. Everybody gets exactly the same.
除了给范・戴恩先生稍微多一点
Except Mr. Van Daan gets a little bit more.
-说谎。她总是平均切。  -范・戴恩先生，请不要这样
- That's a lie. She always cuts the same. - Mr. Van Daan, please.
你看，米耶普，一小块糖蛋糕把我们弄成什么样了？
You see, Miep, what a little sugar cake does to us?
我们都迷住了
It goes right to our heads.
-给你，弗兰克太太。  -谢谢
- Here you are, Mrs. Frank. - Thank you.
-你肯定一点也不要？  -肯定
- You sure you won't have any? - Very sure.
-米耶普？ -真的不要，谢谢
- Miep? - No, thank you. Really.
-切蛋糕。  -好
-Cut the cake. - All right.
谢谢，彼得
Thank you, Peter.
这是你的，彼得
That's yours, Peter.
或许毛刺回来了
Maybe Mouschi went back to our house.
你在那熬过吗？你认为你能吗？
Do you ever get over there? Do you think that you could?
我恐怕在毛刺离开的一星期，彼得......
I'm afraid with him gone a week, Peter...
你就死心吧。有人已经把毛只猫当做腹中餐了
Make up your mind. Already someone has had a big nice meal from that cat.
-嗯，真好吃，米耶普。  -好吃
- Mmm, it's delicious, Miep. - Delicious.
那么，我必须走了，晚上有个聚会
Well, I must run. There's a party tonight.
太棒了
How heavenly.
记住每个人穿的......
Remember now what everyone's wearing...
每一样你吃的，明天好告诉我们
and what you have to eat and everything so you can tell us tomorrow.
我会向你详细汇报。再见，各位
I'll give you a full report. Good-bye, everyone.
-再见。  -再见，米耶普
- Good-bye. - Good-bye, Miep.
嘿，等一下。有件事要你帮一下
Hey,just a minute. There's something I'd like you to do for me.
普提，你要去哪？
Putti, where are you going?
普提，你要做什么？
Putti, what are you gonna do?
普提
Putti.
不，不，不。你怎么敢拿那件大衣
No, no, no. Don't you dare take that coat.
有什么不对劲吗？
What is wrong?
爸爸说他要卖了她的真皮大衣
father says he's gonna sell her fur coat.
因为那件大衣，她都发疯了
She's crazy about that old fur coat.
-那是我的。我爸爸留给我的大衣。  -给我大衣
-It's mine. My father gave me that coat. -I want the coat.
-你，你没有权利。  -把手松开
- No, you have no right. - Get your hands off it.
还有人会......傻到......
Is it possible that anyone can... be silly enough...
在这种时候操心一件真皮大衣？
to worry about a fur coat at a time like this?
不关你的事
It's none of your darn business.
-要是你再说一次......  -彼得
- And if you say one more thing... - Peter.
只是......
Just a...
讨论了一下卖这件大衣的事情
little discussion on the advisability of selling this coat.
我常常提醒范・戴恩太太......
As I have often reminded Mrs. Van Daan...
外面还有那么多需要衣服的人，留着大衣是很自私的
it's selfish to keep it when people outside are in such need of clothing.
所以，你看能不能帮我卖了大衣
So if you please to sell it for us.
会卖个好价钱
It should fetch a good price.
顺便说一下，能帮我带些烟吗？
And by the way, would you get me cigarettes?
我不在乎什么烟。能弄到的尽管弄
I don't care what kind they are. Get all you can.
很难弄到，范・戴恩先生
It is very difficult to get them, Mr. Van Daan.
不过我会试试。再见
But I will try. Good-bye.
-再见。  -再见，米耶普
- Good-bye. - Bye, Miep.
弗兰克先生，可以和你谈谈吗？
Mr. Frank, could I talk to you?
发生什么事情了吗，卡勒先生？发生什么事情了？
Something's happened, hasn't it, Mr. Kraler? What's happened?
是一件与这里的人相关的事情，我们最好都听听
If it is something that concerns us here, we'd better all hear it.
-孩子们......  -他们想象的......
- The children... - What they'd imagine...
会比任何现实都变得更糟
would be worse than any reality.
有一个男人在储藏室。他叫卡尔。你认识他
It is a man in the storeroom. His name is Karl. You knew him.
有一天他来到办公室。他关上门然后问我......
One day he came to the office. He closed the door and asked me...
“你有你的朋友弗兰克先生的消息吗？”
"What do you hear from your friend Mr. Frank?"
我告诉他有传闻说你在瑞士
I told him there was a rumor that you were in Switzerland.
他说他也听到传闻了，但是他认为我了解得更多
He said he had heard that rumor too, but he thought I might know something more.
我没当回事。我......我尽力把那件事忘了
I did not pay much attention. I... I tried to forget it.
然后昨天......
And then yesterday...
我们走出储藏室
we were coming out of the storeroom out there.
下楼去办公室
I had started down to the office.
我回头一看
I looked back.
他正站着，盯着书架
He was standing, staring at the bookcase.
他说，“我想我记得有个门通到这儿。
He said, "I thought I remember a door up here.
这儿没有门通向阁楼吗？”
Was not there a door here leading to the loft?"
然后他向我要更多的钱。一周加二十吉尔特
Then he asked me for more money. Twenty gilders more a week.
-敲诈。  -二十吉尔特？适度的敲诈
- Blackmail. - Twenty gilders? Very modest blackmail.
那才刚刚开始
That's just the beginning.
你知道我怎么想吗？
You know what I think?
他就是那天晚上来楼下的窃贼
He's the thief who was down there that night.
那就是为什么他知道我们在这里
That's how he knows we're here.
会怎样啊？你怎样答复他的？
How was it left? What did you tell him?
我告诉他我考虑一下
I told him I had to think about it.
我该怎么办？给他钱？
What shall I do? Pay him the money?
找个机会解雇他，还是怎么的？
Take a chance on firing him or what?
-我不知道。  -看在老天份上，别解雇他
- I do not know. - For heaven's sakes, don't fire him.
把他要的给他。让他留在这，你好盯着他
Pay him what he asks. Keep him here where you can keep your eye on him.
是不是他要的太多了？我是说，现今的工钱应该是多少？
Is it so much that he is asking? I mean, what are they paying nowadays?
-他在兵工厂能赚到那么多。  -啊哈
- He could get it in a war plant. - Mm-hmm.
但这不是兵工厂。注意，我不知道他是否知道情况
But this is not a war plant. Mind you, I do not know if he knows or not.
给他一半。然后我们就知道是不是敲诈了
Offer him half, then we'll soon know if it is blackmail or not.
要真是敲诈，我们就得付钱，对吗？
And if it is, we've gotta pay, haven't we?
无论他要什么，我们都得给
Whatever he asks, we've gotta pay.
事到临头再决定吧
Let us decide that when the time comes.
或许只是我多虑了
This may be all my imagination.
现在大家都到怀疑每个人，每件事的地步了
You get to a point these days where you suspect everyone and everything.
假期的电话铃声是怎么回事？
What does that mean, the telephone ringing on a holiday?
那是我妻子。我告诉她我在办公室里看些文件......That's my wife. I told her I had to go over some papers in my office...
她是从教堂出来给我打的电话
to call me here when she got out of church.
-再见。  -再见
- Good-bye. - Good-bye.
新年快乐
Happy New Year.
再见。  -再见，卡勒先生
-Good-bye. - Good-bye, Mr. Kraler.
我要先付他一半
I will offer him half then.
谢谢，卡勒先生
Thank you, Mr. Kraler.
多谢你儿子做的一切
Thank your son for this.
他和他该死的猫。那天晚上。在那儿
Him and his damn cat. That night. There.
我告诉你，那只是，只是，只是，只是个时间问题
I tell you, it's...it's...it's... it's just a question of time now.
有时候我真希望结局快点来，不管是什么样的
Sometimes I wish the end would come, whatever it is.
-玛戈特！  -那样至少我们会知道我们在哪里
- Margot! - Then at least we'd know where we were.
你应该对自己感到害臊。说出那种话
You should be ashamed of yourself, talking that way.
想想我们多幸运
Think how lucky we are.
想想每天千千万万战争中死去的人
Think of the thousands dying in the war every day.
-想想集中营里的人。  -那有什么好处？
- Think of the people in camps. - What's the good of that?
当你已经很悲惨了，再想那些悲惨有什么好处？
What's the good of thinking of misery when you're already miserable?
太蠢了
That's stupid.
我们还年轻。玛戈特，彼得还有我
We're young, Margot and Peter and I.
你们大人都有过你们的机会
You grown-ups have had your chance.
看看我们。要是我们开始去想世上所有的可怕，我们就毁了
Look at us. If we begin thinking of all the horror in the world, we're lost.
我们都努力把握住某种理想......
We're trying to hold on to some kind of ideals...
当一切――理想，希望――一切都在毁掉的时候
when everything-- ideals, hope-- everything is being destroyed.
世界如此混乱并不是我们的错
It isn't our fault the world is in such a mess.
一切开始的时候我们还没有到来
We weren't around when all this started.
-现在听我说。  -不要试图从我们身上剥夺。
- Now you listen to me. - So don't try to take it out on us.
她的口气好像是我们发动的战争
She talks as if we started the war.
我们发动战争了吗？
Did we start the war?
你忘拿这个了
You left this.
谢谢
Thanks.
我感觉你刚才说的很好
I thought you were fine just now.
你知道如何和他们讲话。我都不能想象什么时候会发疯
You know just how to talk to 'em. I can never think when I'm mad.
我说的太多了
I say too much.
我伤了他们的心
I hurt people's feelings.
我想你做的很好
I think you're just fine.
谢谢，彼得
Thank you, Peter.
那个达索尔，他说的毛刺那些话，什么有人把它吃了之类......
That Dussel, what he said about Mouschi, about somebody eating him...
我想做的就是揍他
all I could think is I wanted to hit him.
我过去在学校常常那样，但是.....
That's what I used to do in school, but...
这里争吵一开始，我只是在我屋里躲着
here a fight starts, I just duck in my room.
你很幸运还有个房间去呢
You're lucky having a room to go to.
他那大驾总是在我房间里
His Lordship is always in mine.
每当他进来的时候，我都得站起来让路
When they start in on me, I have to stand and take it.
你刚把一部分还给他们
You gave some of it back to them just now.
我疯了
I get so mad.
他们对什么事
They've formed their opinions.
都已经有成见了
About everything.
但是我们还在试图找出
But we're still trying to find out.
我们在这儿遇到的问题，是和我们一样大的人从来没遇到过的
We have problems here that no other people our age have ever had.
你刚以为你已经解决了问题......
And just as you think you've solved them...
就又有事情冒出来，砰......
something comes along and, bang...
你还得从头再来
you have to start all over again.
我认为你爸爸很好
I think your father's fine.
哦，是的，彼得，他是很好
Oh, he is, Peter. He is.
他是唯一一个让我感觉我还是一个有意义的人
He's the only one who's ever given me the feeling that I have any sense.
我和你，不可笑吗？
Isn't it funny, you and I?
在这里虽然我们一直在一起......
Here we've been together all this time...
这还是我们第一次真正谈话
and this is the first time we've ever really talked.
和人谈话还是很有益处的，不是吗？
It helps a lot to have someone to talk to, doesn't it?
可以帮助你释放心情
It helps you let off steam.
不管什么时候......
Any time that...
你想要发泄的时候......
you want to let off steam...
你可以来我屋里
you can come into my room.
我可以攒很多很多郁闷
I can get up an awful lot of steam.
那对我无所谓
It's all right with me.
真的吗？
Do you mean that?
我不是说了吗？
I said it, didn't I?
-晚安。  -晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
-我可以进来吗？  -不，达索尔先生。我还没穿衣服
- May I come in? - No, Mr. Dussel. I'm not dressed yet.
哦
Oh.
-玛戈特。  -啊？
- Margot. - Hmm?
告诉我，我是不是很丑啊？
Tell me, am I terribly ugly?
-哦，别问了。  -不，告诉我
- Oh, stop fishing. - No. Tell me.
你当然不丑。你有一双漂亮的眼睛......
Of course you're not. You've got nice eyes...
并且很活泼，并且......并且......
and a lot of animation and...and...
-我可以进来吗？  -进来，妈妈
- May I come in? - Come in, Mother.
达索尔先生要进来，都等的不耐烦了
Mr. Dussel is impatient to get in here.
他整天自己占着房间
He takes the room for himself the entire day.
你不打算今晚再去见彼得吗，嗯？
You're not going in again tonight to see Peter, hmm?
我是那么想的
That is my intention.
你不怕打扰他？
Aren't you afraid you're disturbing him?
妈妈，我有分寸
Mother, I have some intuition.
那么我多说点行吗，安娜？
Then may I ask this much, Annie?
你进去后请不要关上门
Please don't shut the door when you go in.
你真象范・戴恩太太
You sound like Mrs. Van Daan.
哦，不。我这是为你好
Oh, no. I don't mean to suggest anything wrong.
我只是希望你不要受到责备
I only wish you wouldn't expose yourself to criticism.
对不起，妈妈。我要去彼得那里了
I'm sorry, Mother. I'm going to Peter's room.
我可不想让彼得罗妮拉・范・戴恩毁了我们的友谊
I'm not going to let Petronella Van Daan spoil our friendship.
稍等，达索尔先生
Just a moment, Mr. Dussel.
在我那时候都是男孩拜访女孩的
In my day the boys called on the girls.
你了解年轻人
You know how young people are.
彼得的房间是唯一能谈话的地方
Peter's room is the only place they can talk.
谈话？
Talk?
我还是个女孩的时候，他们可不那么叫
That's not what they called it when I was a girl.
抱歉，玛戈特，，又得你自己呆着了
I'm sorry, Margot, that you have to be the one left out.
我对你很内疚
I feel so guilty about you.
为什么？
Why?
我是说，每次我去彼得那里......
I mean, every time I go to Peter...
我在彼得房间的时候，都感觉伤害你了
into Peter's room, I have the feeling that I'm hurting you.
我知道要是我的话，会嫉妒死的
I know if it were me, I'd be desperately jealous.
我是有点嫉妒
I am jealous a little.
不是你和彼得
Not of you and Peter.
我......
I'm...
我只是遗憾没有任何人......
I'm only feeling sorry that I haven't anyone...
和我讨论我的感情
with whom to-- to discuss my feelings.
玛戈特，我甚至不会......
Margot, I won't even...
听着，你找到了友谊，我要你好好享受
Listen, you've found a companionship, and I want you to enjoy it.
只是在我心里，我感觉有权和别人分享我的感情
Only in my heart I feel I've got a right to share feelings with someone too.
但是我肯定彼得......那个男孩，不是我要的那种人
But I'm sure that Peter... that that boy, he could never be that person for me.
或许没有什么可嫉妒的
Maybe there's nothing to be jealous about.
或许我只是替代了他猫的位置
Maybe I'm just taking the place of his cat.
可以让我进我的房间吗？
Will you please let me in my room?
稍等，亲爱的，亲爱的达索尔先生
Just a minute, dear, dear Mr. Dussel.
好了，我走了......
Well, here I go...
去受他们夹攻了
to run the gauntlet.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
看她
Look at her.
养个儿子真有好处。我从来见不到他
A lot of good it did me to have a son. I never see him.
稍等，亲爱的
Just a minute, dear.
我想和我儿子说几句话，你介意吗？
I'd like to say a few words to my son. Do you mind?
彼得，我不想要你整夜不睡觉
Peter, I do not want you staying up till all hours tonight.
你需要睡眠，你正在长身体
You need your sleep. You are a growing boy.
安妮不可以呆的太晚。她必须九点钟睡觉
Anne won't stay late. She's going to bed promptly at 9:00.
-不是吗，安妮？  -是的，妈妈，我可以走了吗？
- Aren't you, Anne? - Yes, Mother. May we go now?
你听敲钟就可以，亲爱的
Listen for the chimes, dear.
难道可能吗？
Aren't they impossible?
待我们就好像我们还在保育室里
Treating us as if we're still in the nursery.
别让它烦你了......它并没有让我烦
Don't let it bother you. It...It doesn't bother me.
我想你真的不能怪他们
I suppose you can't really blame them.
他们总是回忆他们在我们这么大时候的一举一动
They think back to what they were like at our age.
他们意识不到我们已经进步多少了
They don't realize how much more advanced we are.
我已经知道自己该做什么了。你呢?
Already I know what I want to do. Don't you?
我想做个记者什么的
I want to be a journalist or something.
我喜欢作家
I love to write.
你要做什么
What do you want to do?
我现在知道我要做什么
I know what I'd like right now.
我想去英国，和自由荷兰力量在一起
I'd like to make it to England, get with the Free Dutch Forces over there.
彼得，你不可以做那种事
Peter, you wouldn't try a thing like that.
-你不会做。  -我会的
- You'd never make it. - I'd make it.
那只是我想做的无数事情中的其中一个
Only a few of the hundreds that try do.
我知道，但是......我想加入进去，然后打回来
I know, but... I'd like to get in it and-- and hit back.
就坐在这儿，那可不是我
To just sit here, it's not for me.
你喜欢玛戈特吗？
You like Margot, don't you?
开始你喜欢她
Right from the start you liked her.
比起我你更喜欢她
Liked her better than me.
哦，我不知道
Oh, I don't know.
是那样
It's all right.
大家都是那么想的
Everyone feels that way.
玛戈特那么好
Margot's so good.
她甜蜜，聪明又漂亮，我都不是
She's sweet and bright and beautiful, and I'm not.
我没那么说啊
I wouldn't say that.
哦，不，我都不是。我知道的
Oh, no, I'm not. I know that.
我十分清楚我不漂亮
I know quite well that I'm not a beauty.
过去，将来都不漂亮
I never have been and never shall be.
我绝对不同意
I don't agree at all.
我想你很漂亮
I think you're pretty.
那不是真话
That's not true.
再有一件事
A...And another thing.
你变了，我的意思是，从开始就变了
You've changed. From the first, I mean.
我变了？
I have?
我过去认为你太吵闹了
I used to think that you were awful noisy.
你现在怎么想的，彼得？
And what do you think now, Peter?
我变成什么样了？
How have I changed?
嗯，你......
Well, you...
你更文静了
You're quieter.
我很高兴你不讨厌我
I'm glad you don't just hate me.
我从来没那么说过啊
I never said that.
我敢打赌只要你从这出去，你就会永远忘了我
I bet when you get out of here, you'll never think of me again.
真是疯了
That's crazy.
当你带着你的朋友们回来......
When you get back with all your friends...
你会说......
you're going to say...
“现在我真不知道为什么我会喜欢那个呱呱小姐？”
"Now what did I ever see in that Miss Quack-Quack?"
-我没有朋友。  -彼得，你当然有
- I haven't got any friends. - Peter, of course you have.
每个人都有朋友
Everyone has friends.
不包括我，我一个也没有
Not me. I don't want any.
没有朋友我也过的很好
I get along fine without 'em.
你的意思是不是没有我，你也过得很好啊？
Does that mean you can get along without me too?
我把自己当成你的朋友
I think of myself as your friend.
不
No.
如果他们都喜欢你......
If they were all like you...
那就不同了
it'd be different.
-彼得。  -啊？
- Peter... - Hmm?
你吻过女孩子吗？
Did you ever kiss a girl?
是的
Yes.
一次
Once.
她漂亮吗？
Was she pretty?
那个你吻过的女孩
The girl you kissed.
我不知道。我被蒙住眼睛了
I don't know. I was blindfolded.
那是在一个聚会。一个亲吻游戏
It was at a party. One of those kissing games.
哦
Oh.
我想那并不算数，对吗？
I don't suppose that really counts, does it?
对于我可不算数了
It didn't with me.
我吻过两次
I've been kissed twice.
一次是一个我从没见过的男人吻我的脸蛋......
Once a man I'd never seen before kissed me on the cheek...
当他把我从冰上拉起来的时候
when he picked me up off the ice.
我那时在哭
I was crying.
另外一次是我父亲的一个朋友，吻我的手
And the other was a friend of father's who kissed my hand.
你不会说不算数吧，是吗？
You wouldn't say those counted, would you?
不会的
I wouldn't say so.
我知道几乎毫无疑问......
I know almost for certain...
玛戈特永远不会吻任何人，除非和他订婚
Margot would never kiss anyone unless she was engaged to them.
我也肯定妈妈在爸爸之前也从来没碰过男人
And I'm sure too that Mother never touched a man before father.
但是我不知道
But I don't know.
现在什么都变了
Things are so different now.
你怎么想？
What do you think?
你是不是认为一个女孩不该吻一个人......
Do you think a girl shouldn't kiss anyone...
除了和她订婚了什么的
except if she's engaged or something?
想想该怎么做太难了......
It's so hard to try to think what to do...
在这里，当我们伴着整个世界在耳边坍塌时
when here we are with the whole world falling around our ears.
那么你想......
And you think...
你看，你不知道明天会怎样
well, you don't know what's going to happen tomorrow.
你是怎么想的?
What do you think?
嗯，呃......
Well, uh...
我想，那得看女孩的
I suppose it...it depends on the girl.
对于一些女孩来说，无......无论他们做什么，都是错的
With some, n-no matter what they do, it's wrong.
而另一些......
But others...
怎样做都没有错
it wouldn't necessarily be wrong with them.
我过去总想......
I always thought that...
当两个人......
when two people--
我想我该走了
I think I should go now.
是的
That's right.
晚安
Good night.
-不要让他们阻止你来。  -不会的
-You won't let 'em stop you from coming? -No.
我要把日记带来
I might bring my diary.
里面有太多我要和你谈论的东西了
There are so many things in it I want to talk over with you.
有很多关于你的
There's a lot about you.
什么内容啊？
What kind of things?
呃......
Well...
有些我不想让你看
I wouldn't want you to see some of it.
我过去认为你什么都不是
I thought you were nothing.
就像你对我的看法似的
Just the way you thought about me.
你是不是已经改变了对我的看法......
Did you change your mind...
就像我改变了对你的看法一样？
the way I changed my mind about you?
噢，你会知道的
Well, you'll see.
晚安，安妮
Good night, Annele.
-晚安，天使。  -晚安
- Good night, angel. - Good night.
啊哈
Mm-hmm.
在外面弥漫着静悄悄的兴奋
Outside there is a quiet excitement.
盟军占领症的热度也一天天在这里升高
Invasion fever is mounting from day to day.
人们除了谈论解放的希望，什么也不说了
And people talk of nothing else but the hope of liberation.
解放最好快点到来
It had best come soon.
我们也有坏消息
We here have had bad news.
给米耶普提供定量供应证的人被捕了
The people from whom Miep got our ration cards have been arrested.
卡勒先生住院了
Mr. Kraler is in the hospital.
好像他得了溃疡
It seems he has ulcers.
我恐怕我们就是他的溃疡
I'm afraid we are his ulcers.
米耶普得处理公事，还得照看我们
Miep has to run the business and us too.
我们真的太幸运了......
How very fortunate we are...
当想到外面发生的一切的时候
when you think of what is happening outside.
我感觉春天正在到来
I feel that spring is coming.
我感觉春天充满了我的身体和灵魂
I feel it in my whole body and soul.
我彻底迷茫了
I'm utterly confused.
我一直渴望...渴望着一切
I am longing...so longing for everything.
奥托！奥托，快。他在偷食物
Otto! Otto, quick. He's stealing the food!
-埃蒂茨，埃蒂茨！  -范・戴恩先生，让我看看！
- Edith, Edith! - Mr. Van Daan, let me see that!
范・戴恩先生，过来...... 让我......
Mr. Van Daan, come... Let me...
-给我......  -发生什么事了？范・戴恩先生。范......
- Give me... - What happened? Mr. Van Daan. Mr....
看，面包！
Look, the bread!
你这个肮脏的贼
You dirty thief.
-你这个废物。 -放开他。救救我，彼得
- You good-for-nothing. - Let him go. Help me, Peter.
放开他！彼得，救救我！
Let him go! Peter, help me!
放开他！
Let him go!
普提，那是什么？
Putti, what is it?
他在偷面包
He was stealing the bread.
是你啊。我们还都一直以为是老鼠偷的
It was you. And all the time we thought it was the rats.
范・戴恩先生，你怎么能这样？
Mr. Van Daan, how could you?
-我饿啊。  -我们都饿
- I'm hungry. - We're all of us hungry.
我看着孩子们越来越瘦
I see the children getting thinner and thinner.
你自己的儿子，我听到他在梦中呻吟，他太饿了
Your own son, I've heard him moan in his sleep, he's so hungry.
你却下来偷食物，那些应该给孩子们的食物
And you come down and steal food that should go to them, the children.
他比我们需要更多的食物
He needs more food than the rest of us.
他吃得多，他太胖了
He's used to more. He's a big man.
你！
And you!
你比他更坏。你是一个母亲
You're worse than he is. You're a mother.
为了这个人，你竟然牺牲你自己的儿子，这个......这个......
And yet you sacrifice your son to this man, this...this...
埃蒂茨
Edith.
别以为我没看到你
Don't think I haven't seen you.
总是挑出最好的那点留给他。我一直盯着你呢
Always saving the choicest bits for him. I've watched you.
多少天了，我忍着没说，现在不忍了
Day after day, and I've held my tongue, but not any longer.
以后再也不忍了
Not after this!
现在我要他离开。我要他从这里出去
Now I want him to go. I want him to get out of here!
埃蒂茨
Edith.
从这出去？
Get out of here?
-你是什么意思？  -就这样，拿着你的东西，出去
- What do you mean? -Just that. Take your things. Get out.
你在说气话。你不是那意思
You're speaking in anger. You cannot mean what you're saying.
-就是那意思。  -两年了，我们生活在一起
-I mean exactly that. -For 2 years we have lived side by side.
我们尊重彼此的权利
We have respected each other's rights.
我们努力和平相处。我们现在要全都丢弃吗？
We have managed to live in peace. Are we going to throw it all away?
范・戴恩先生......
Mr. Van Daan...
我知道这种事再也不会发生了。是不是？
I know this is never going to happen again, is it?
-不会了，不会了  -哈，偷一次，还会偷第二次
- No, no. - Ah, he steals once, he'll steal again.
我要他们离开。现在就走
I want them to leave. You go now!
妈妈
Mother.
你要把彼得也撵出去？他什么也没做啊
You're not putting Peter out? Peter hasn't done anything.
我不是说彼得。他可以呆在这里
I don't mean Peter. Peter can stay.
要是他走我也得走。他是我爸爸
I'll have to go if he goes. That's my father.
他不配做你爸爸，那个人
He's no father to you, that man.
他不知道爸爸意味着什么
He doesn't know what it means to be a father.
感觉不合适。我不能留在这
I wouldn't feel right. I couldn't stay.
那么好吧
Very well then.
彼得，不
Peter. No.
弗兰克太太，你要把我们赶到大街上吗？
Mrs. Frank, you would put us out in the street?
你们可以再找一个藏身之处
You can find another hiding place.
我们去哪里找一个地窖......一个壁橱啊？
Where would we even find a cellar... a-a closet?
弗兰克先生......
Mr. Frank...
你告诉普提......
you told Putti...
你不会忘了吧，当你刚来到荷兰的时候，他是怎么对你的
you would never forget what he did for you when you first came to Holland.
你说过你永远都报答不了他
You said you never would be able to repay him.
要是我丈夫有什么欠你的，他已经加倍偿还了
If my husband had any obligations to you, he has paid it over and over.
埃蒂茨，我不明白。我从来没见你这样
Edith, I don't know you. I've never seen you like this.
我早就该说出来了
I should have spoken out long ago.
你对有些人没好处
You can't be nice to some people.
如果你不来这，本来我们会有足够的东西
There would have been plenty for all of us if you hadn't come in here!
不，不，范・戴恩太太。
No, no, Mrs. Van Daan. Please.
我们不必纳粹毁掉我们了
We don't need the Nazis to destroy us.
我们自己就毁掉自己了
We're destroying ourselves.
妈妈，请不要让他们离开
Mother, please don't send them away.
-已经天亮了。  -他们会被抓住的
- It's daylight. - And they'll be caught.
-最高统帅部......  -他们现在不用走
-Supreme headquarters... - They're not going now.
他们可以留到米耶普为他们找到躲藏的地方
They'll stay until Miep finds them a place to hide.
弗兰克太太，弗兰克先生，玛戈特
Mrs. Frank, Mr. Frank, Margot.
不，不，不
Oh, no, no.
我们不能堕落到为了食物，自己人都打起来的地步
We haven't sunk so low that we're gonna fight amongst ourselves over food.
那是安妮。那是范・戴恩太太范・戴恩先生，
That's Anne. That's Mrs. Van Daan, Mr. Van Daan.
你看到他做什么了吗？
You see what he's doing?
“我仍然守候在此为您带来进一步的占领消息。”
"I'm still standing by to bring you further news of the invasion."
你没听到吗？“为那些没有听到的人，让我再次播报”
Did you hear that? "For those of you who may not have heard, let me repeat.
“在诺曼底海岸，登陆于今晨已经开始。”
"The landings began this morning on the coast of Normandy."
-开始了，听！ -D-Day已经开始。
- It's started. Listen! -D-Day has come.
在夜晚和今天早晨最初几小时......
During the night and in the early hours of this morning...
-一个庞大的舰队......   =听！
- an immense armada... - Listen!
-4000艘船和小艇......   -彼得，我自己
-4,000 ships and smaller craft... -Peter, myself.
-你给自己留了大的。  -没有
- You keep the big ones for yourself. - No.
是的，你留了。所有大的
Yes, you are. All the big ones.
-看那个大的。  -那是我的
- Look at the size of that one. - That's mine.
-看那个。  -那是范・戴恩先生的
- And look at that one. - That's Mr. Van Daan's.
-嗯，看......  -住嘴！住嘴！
- Well, look at... - Stop it! Stop it!
-别数土豆了！  -是米耶普。让我进来
- Stop counting potatoes! - It's Miep. Let me in.
弗兰克先生，弗兰克太太！
Mr. Frank and Mrs. Frank!
达索尔先生，求你不要让她看到这种事
Mr. Dussel, I beg of you, don't let her see a thing like this.
哦，这是......弗兰克太太......
Well, this is... Mrs. Frank...
占领开始了！
The invasion has begun!
最兴奋的消息。占领开始了！
The most wonderful news. The invasion has begun.!
仅是初步消息......
Only preliminary reports have come in...
听到了吗？他们登陆了！
Did you hear? They have landed!
在法国海岸。诺曼底
On the coast of France. In Normandy.
-英国人，美国人。  -他们都来了
- The British, the Americans. -They're all in it.!
荷兰人，法国人，波兰人，挪威人，都来了
Dutch, French, Poles, Norwegians, everyone.
-他们叫做D-Day。   -D-Day
- D-Day they call it. - D-Day.
最后了！噢！
At last! Oh!
-是我，卡勒。  -不可能是卡勒先生
-It's me. Kraler. - It cannot be Mr. Kraler.
的确是卡勒先生
But it is Mr. Kraler.
听到没有？
Did you hear?
太棒了啊
Isn't it wonderful?
当医生告诉我那个消息......
When the nurse told me the news...
我就对自己说只有一个地方我该去......和我的朋友在一起
I said to myself there's only one place for me to be... with my friends.
嘘。嘘
Shh. Shh.
快，在工人来之前。我回头再来
Quick. Before the workmen come. I'll be up later.
-再见，我亲爱的朋友。  -再见，卡勒先生
- Good-bye, my dear friends. - Good-bye, Mr. Kraler.
谢谢你，米耶普
Thank you, Miep.
普提，怎么了？出什么事了？
Putti, what is it? What happened?
我太丢人了！
I am so ashamed!
哦，看在老天的份上
Oh, for heaven's sake.
普提，别这样
Putti, don't.
范・戴恩先生，你没听到吗？
Mr. Van Daan, didn't you hear?
我们快要自由了
We're going to be liberated.
这是庆祝的时刻
This is a time to celebrate.
偷孩子们的面包
To steal bread from children.
哦，我们都做过丢人的事儿
Oh, we've all done things that we're ashamed of.
看我怎样对我妈妈――对她那么吝啬，那么糟糕
Look at the way I treated Mother-- so mean and horrid to her.
不，安妮。不。  -哦，我是那样的。我太坏了
- No, Anneke. No. - Oh, I was, Mother. I was awful.
和我不一样
Not like me.
没有人比我更坏
No one is as bad as me.
鱼雷艇加入到英国军舰当中......
Torpedo boats join British warships...
成千的盟军飞机投下地动山摇的炸弹
and thousands of Allied planes in laying down an earthshaking bombardment.
行了！
Stop it!
让我们高兴起来！
Let's be happy!
埃蒂茨
Edith.
我一想起我说的那些难听的话
When I think of the terrible things I said.
不，不。你说的对
No, no. You were right.
我竟然那样和你们说话......
That I should speak that way to you...
我们的朋友，我们的客人
our friends, our guests.
行了！你们破坏了整个占领行动
Stop it! You're spoiling the whole invasion.
万能的上帝......
Almighty God...
我们的孩子们......
our sons...
国家的骄傲......
pride of our nation...
正在进行一项坚苦卓绝的事业......
this day have set upon a mighty endeavor...
挺起你们的胸膛......
Lift up your hearts.
抑制住悲伤......
Out of the depths of sorrow...
牺牲......
and of sacrifice...
会让人类的光荣重生
will be born again the glory of mankind.
这些天我们的精神都更好了
We are all in much better spirits these days.
不断地有占领的好消息
There is still excellent news of the invasion.
最好的消息就是我感觉朋友们就要来了
And the best part about it is that I have a feeling friends are coming.
我们敬爱的女王宣布
Our beloved queen spoke.
她用了一个词“很快，”
She used words like "soon, '"
“当我回来的时候，”“迅速解放。”
"when I am back, " "speedy liberation. '"
谁知道呢？
Who knows?
或许秋天我就能回到学校了
I may be back in school by fall.
1944年7月2日，星期三
Wednesday, the second of July, 1944.
豹式坦克集团的猛烈反攻......
Fierce counterattacks by enemy panzer divisions...
使占领似乎暂时停顿下来
The invasion seems temporarily bogged down.
卡勒先生回医院了
Mr. Kraler is back in the hospital.
他必须做一个手术
He has to have an operation.
D-Day似乎使他太劳心了
It seems D-Day was too much for him.
-谢谢。  -给你
- Thank you. - Here you are.
哈哈。开了我们一个玩笑
Ha ha. The joke is on us.
米耶普告诉我们储藏室那个人什么也不知道......
Miep tells us the warehouseman doesn't know a thing...
并且我们会付给他所有的钱
and we're paying him all that money.
我们的蔬菜商正在去集中营的路上
Our vegetable man is on his way to a concentration camp.
他今天被抓住藏了两个犹太人
He was picked up today for hiding two Jews in his house.
没有太多消息
There's not much.
那是我们的蔬菜商，豪克先生，他们被捕了
It was Mr. Hauk, our greengrocer, they arrested.
另外一个消息是......
And the other news is...
盖世太保发现我们的打字机丢了
the Gestapo have found our typewriter that was stolen.
-不。  -啊哈
- No. - Uh-huh.
他们会去找打字机，然后找到我们
They'll trace it back and back till it gets to us.
你瞧吧，你......
You watch, you...
每个人都情绪低落
Everyone is low.
就是爸爸也提不起精神
Even father can't raise their spirits.
我常常会沮丧......
I have often been downcast myself...
不过从没绝望
but never in despair.
当我写字的时候，就会忘掉一切，但是......
I can shake oFF everything if I write, but--
这有一个大问题......
and that is the great question...
我写的好吗？
will I ever be able to write well?
我想要的太多了
I want to so much.
我想要我死后还继续活着
I want to go on living even after my death.
又响了
There it goes again.
弗兰克先生。听到没有？
Mr. Frank, do you hear?
是的，听到了
Yes, I hear.
这是第三次了
This is the third time.
连续第三次了
The third time in quick succession.
是一个信号
It's a signal.
我说是米耶普要联系我们
I tell you it's Miep trying to get us.
由于某种原因――她不能过来......
For some reason she-- she can't come to us...
她在试图警告我们什么事
and she's trying to warn us of something.
请不要这样，达索尔先生。
Please, Mr. Dussel. Please.
你在白费口舌
You're wasting your breath.
一定是发生什么事情了。弗兰克先生
Something has happened, Mr. Frank.
米耶普已经三天没来看我们了
It's been three days now that Miep hasn't been to see us.
今天没有一个人来上班
And today not a man has come to work.
楼里面鸦雀无声
There hasn't been a sound in the building.
或许是星期日
Perhaps it's Sunday.
我们或许都没法判断日期了
We may have lost track of the days.
你有这本日记。今天星期几？
You with the diary there, what day is it?
我没忘记日期
I don't lose track of the days.
我知道今天星期几
I know exactly what day it is.
是星期五，八月四日
It's Friday, the fourth of August.
今天星期五，却没有一个人上班
It's Friday, and not a man at work.
告诉你，卡勒先生死了
I tell you, Mr. Kraler is dead.
那是唯一的解释
That's the only explanation.
他死了，这栋楼歇业了......
He's dead, and they've closed down the building...
那就是米耶普试图告诉我们的
and that's what Miep's trying to tell us.
可能她从来没给我们打过电话，达索尔先生
She would never telephone us, Mr. Dussel.
我求你了，弗兰克先生，去接电话
Please, I beg of you, Mr. Frank, answer the phone.
-不  。-接起来就可以。你不必说话
- No. -Just listen. You don't have to speak.
只是听听，看是不是米耶普
Just listen and see if it's Miep.
看在上帝的份上，去接电话！
For God's sake, answer the telephone!
我说了，不
I've told you, no.
我不会做任何事情，让别人知道我们在这栋楼里
I'll do nothing that might let anyone know that we're in this building.
弗兰克先生是正确的
Mr. Frank's right.
不用告诉我们你赞成谁
There's no need to tell us what side you're on.
如果我们就这么安静，耐心地等着，我相信会有帮助到来的
If we wait here quietly and patiently, I believe that help will come.
达索尔先生......
Mr. Dussel...
不，达......达索尔先生......达索尔先生！
No, Mr.... Mr. Dussel... Mr. Dussel!
太迟了
Too late.
就这么一直等着......等到死
So we just wait here... until we die.
我受不了了。我要自杀
I can't stand it. I'll kill myself.
看在老天的份上，别说话
For heaven's sake, stop it.
要是我自杀，你会高兴的。你愿意要我死
I think you would be glad if I did. You want me to die.
我们在这里是谁的错？
Whose fault is it we're here?
我们本来可以在美国或者瑞士很安全
We could have been safe in America or Switzerland.
不，不。我想离开的时候，你却不愿意离开
But no, no. You wouldn't leave when I wanted to.
你舍不得你那些值钱的东西
You couldn't leave your precious things.
-你的家具。  -是那样
- Your furniture. - That's right.
全都怪我。都是我的错
Blame it all on me. It's all my fault.
你的帽子，你的鞋，还有那些碟子
Your hats,your shoes,your dishes.
不就是为了让你过的舒适才弄那些吗
For your comfort we had anything.
-我的舒适。  -我从来没有过我想要的东西
-My comfort. - I never had anything I really wanted.
哪个不是为了让你高兴！
Everything was for your pleasure!
看，彼得。看天空
Look, Peter. Look at the sky.
那些云彩漂亮吧？
Aren't the clouds beautiful?
好好可爱的一天
A lovely, lovely day.
你知道我要做的吗......
You know what I do...
当我无法再忍受哪怕一分钟被关在笼子里的时候
when I think I can't stand another minute of being cooped up?
我想象着我在外面了
I think myself outside.
我想象着我在公园里散步，那个我常和爸爸一起去的......
I think I'm on a walk in the park where I used to go with father...
漫坡都是番红花，长寿花，还有紫罗兰的地方
where the crocus and the jonquils and the violets grow along the slopes.
你知道......
You know...
你想过在外面最美好的是什么吗？
the most wonderful part of thinking yourself outside?
你可以随心所欲做你想要做的
You can have it any way you like.
你可以让玫瑰花，紫罗兰，郁金香都在一个季节里开放
You can have roses, violets and tulips all blooming in the same season.
多美妙啊！
Isn't that wonderful?
当我以前在外面的时候，我一直认为什么都理所当然
When I was outside, I used to take it all for granted.
现在在这里，一想到大自然，我都要疯了
And now in here I've just gone crazy about nature.
我已经疯了
I've just gone crazy.
我想要是不快点发生什么......
I think if something doesn't happen soon...
要是我们不能出去......
if we don't get out of here...
我就再也受不了了
I can't stand much more of this.
我希望你信仰宗教，彼得
I wish you had a religion, Peter.
不，谢谢
No, thanks.
我不信
Not me.
我不是要你信正教......
I don't mean you have to be Orthodox...
或者信什么天堂，地狱，炼狱之类
or believe in heaven and hell and purgatory and things.
我只是说某个宗教
I just mean some religion.
不管是什么教
It doesn't matter what.
只是信点什么
Just to believe in something.
当我想着所有外面的......
When I think of all that's out there...
树和花......
the trees and flowers...
那些海鸥......
and those seagulls--
当我想着你的可爱，彼得......
When I think of the dearness of you, Peter...
想着我认识的所有善良的人......
and the goodness of the people we know--
卡勒先生和米耶普，那个蔬菜商......
Mr. Kraler and Miep, the vegetable man...
所有那些人都为了我们的生活冒险......
all of them risking their lives for us every day...
当我想着这些美好的时候，我不再害怕了
When I think of these good things, I'm not afraid anymore.
我发现自己......
I find myself...
信主，并且我......
in God, and I...
那......那真好，不过......
That's... That's fine, but...
当我开始想的时候......，嗯......
When I begin to think, well...
我就会发疯
I get mad.
看看我们
Look at us.
藏在这里两年了
Hiding out here for two years.
不能动。就好像......
Not able to move. Caught like...
等着他们来抓我们似的
Waiting for them to come and get us.
我们不是唯一被迫忍受苦难的人
We're not the only people that have had to suffer.
还有很多人不得不忍受
There have always been people that have had to.
有时候是这个民族，有时候是另一个，但是......
Sometimes one race, sometimes another, and yet...
这并没有让我减少痛苦
That doesn't make me feel any better.
我知道那很糟糕，一直努力树立信心......
I know it's terrible, trying to have any faith...
就在人们做着可怕的事情当中......
when people are doing such horrible...
但是你知道我有时候怎么想吗？
But you know what I sometimes think?
我想世界是要经过一个阶段的......
I think the world may be going through a phase...
就像我和妈妈经过的那个阶段一样
the way I was with Mother.
一定会过去的
It'll pass.
也许用不了几百年......
Maybe not for hundreds of years...
总有一天
but someday.
我仍然相信......
I still believe...
尽管发生着每件事......
in spite of everything...
人的内心深处还是善良的
that people are really good at heart.
我就想看到现在......
I want to see something now...
而不是一千年后的什么
not a thousand years from now.
但是，彼得......
But, Peter...
如果你只把它当做一个大图案的一部分......
if you'd only look at it as part of a great pattern...
那也只是我们生命中的一小会儿
that we're just a little minute in life.
听我们说，彼此努力像一对愚蠢的大人吧
Listen to us, going at each other like a couple of stupid grown-ups.
看天空
Look at the sky.
多可爱啊！
Isn't it lovely?
总有一天，当我们再次出去的时候......
Someday, when we get outside again...
我要......
I'm going to...
在过去的两年中，我们生活在恐惧里
For the past two years we have lived in fear.
现在我们生活在希望里
Now we can live in hope.
看来我们呆在这里的日子结束了
And so it seems our stay here is over.
他们只给了我们一点时间收拾东西
They've given us just a moment to get our things.
我们每个人可以带一个包......
We can each take a bag...
只能装衣服
and whatever it will hold of clothing.
其他的不可以
Nothing else.
亲爱的......日记......
So, dear... Diary...
那就是说，我只能把你留下了
that means I must leave you behind.
要告别一段时间了
Good-bye for a while.
附言：任何人......
P.S. Please, please, anyone...
如果发现这本日记......
if you should find this diary...
可以为我保管好吗......
will you please keep it safe for me...
因为我希望有一天......
because someday I hope that...
没有了
No more.
我去乡下试图找些食品
I had gone to the country to try to find food.
当我回来的时候，警察就在楼里了
When I got back, the police were in the building.
我们特意去查他们是怎样知道的
We made it our business to learn how they knew.
是那个窃贼告发的
It was the thief who told them.
我们认识那个窃贼。他是......
We know the thief. He was...
现在对我来说很奇怪......
It seems strange to me now...
我们在集中营里充满了希望，因为是呆在在荷兰，他们抓走我们的地方
but we were so full of hope in the camp in Holland where they first took us.
战争消息都很好
The news of the war was good.
英国人和美国人横扫法国
The British and Americans were sweeping through France.
我们感觉他们会及到达......
We felt sure they would get to us in time to--
但是......
But...
在9月份我们被船运到波兰
in September we were shipped to Poland.
男人去了一个集中营，女人去了另一个
The men to one camp, the women to another.
从那里......他们被送到贝尔森
From there... they were sent to Belsen.
我留在了奥斯维辛
I stayed in Auschwitz.
一月份我们自由了，就我们很少几个幸存的人
In January we were freed, the few of us who were left.
战争当时还没有结束，没有
The war was not yet over, no.
我们花了很长时间才回到家
It took us a long time to get home.
每次火车停下来的时候，我们......
Each time the train would stop, we'd...
全都下去，你知道，沿着人群或穿过去......
all get out, you know, at a siding or a crossing, and...
走过一群群的人
walk from group to group.
“你过去在哪里？”
"Where were you?"
“你过去在贝尔森吗？”
"Were you at Belsen?"
“是在布痕瓦尔德吗？”
"At Buchenwald?"
“在茅斯奥森？哪里？”
"At Mauthausen? Where?"
“有没有可能知道我妻子啊？”
"Is it possible that you ever knew my wife?"
“是不是曾经见过我丈夫，我儿子......
"Did you ever see my husband, my son...
我女儿？”
my daughter?"
我就是那样才知道我妻子已经去世了......
That's how I found out about my wife's death...
玛戈特，范・戴恩夫妇......
Margot's, Van Daans'...
还有彼得，达索尔
Peter, Dussel.
但是......
But...
安妮......
Anne......
我仍然希望......
I still hoped...
昨天我在鹿特丹
Yesterday I was in Rotterdam.
在那遇到一个女人
I met a woman there.
她曾经在贝尔森......和安妮一起
She'd been in Belsen... with Anne.
我现在知道了
I know now.
尽管发生着每件事......
In spite of everything...
我仍然相信，人的内心深处还是善良的
I still believe that people are really good at heart.
她让我脸红
She puts me to shame.